<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble appeale to the Kings most excellent Maiestie Wherein is proued, that our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ, was authour of the Catholike Roman faith, which Protestants call Papistrie. Written by Iohn Hunt, a Roman Catholike, in defence of his religion against the calumniations and persecutions of Protestant ministers.</title>
            <author>Doughty, Thomas, fl. 1618-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7072.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851455</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851455</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16729</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16729)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1603:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble appeale to the Kings most excellent Maiestie Wherein is proued, that our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ, was authour of the Catholike Roman faith, which Protestants call Papistrie. Written by Iohn Hunt, a Roman Catholike, in defence of his religion against the calumniations and persecutions of Protestant ministers.</title>
                  <author>Doughty, Thomas, fl. 1618-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 86, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Birchley Hall Press?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Lancashire :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>John Hunt is a pseudonym for Thomas Doughty.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly identified as STC 13986.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 13986 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; cropt, affecting imprint date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16729:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN HVMBLE APPEALE TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is proued, that our Lord and Sauiour <hi>IESVS CHRIST, was Authour of the Catholike Roman Faith, which Proteſtants call PAPISTRIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>IOHN HVNT,</hi> a Roman Catholike, <hi>in defence of his Religion againſt the Calumniations</hi> and perſecutions of Proteſtant <hi>MINISTERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN</hi> 5. 39.</bibl> Search the Scriptures, for you thinke by them to haue life euerlaſting, and the ſame are they, which giue teſtimonie of mee.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:16729:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16729:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16729:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:16729:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt dread Soueraigne:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O heauy, for many yeares, hath been the hand of Proteſtant Miniſters, vpon vs Catholikes, your auncient and faithfull ſubiects, that heauen is ful with our cries, the world with our afflictions; the earth is drunk with our bloud, the aire a receptacle for our quarters; priſons are filled with our bodies, and Purſuiuants, infamous men, at their pleaſures inriched with the ſpoile of our goods; in ſuch ſort, as with the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> liuing in like perſecution, we may truly ſay: <hi>Wee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 9.</note> 
               <hi>are made a ſpectacle to the world, and to Angels, and to men:</hi> that the extremity of our afflictions enforceth vs to Appeale vnto your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> proſtrate at your feet, in moſt humble manner, to beſeech your Highneſſe to heare the truth of our cauſe, and take notice of the ſincerity of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to <hi>God,</hi> your Perſon and State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> Almighty out of his infinit goodneſſe hauing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs, <hi>according to his owne Image,</hi> and after our fall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 27.</note> redeemed vs from eternall paines; in token of homage, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth of vs the practiſing and profeſſing of that Faith and Religion, which was planted vpon earth by his only Son our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and that with ſuch rigor; as whoſoeuer at his death ſhalbe found faultie herein, ſhall not onely loſe the inheritance of the kingdome of heauen, and the happie viſion of his diuine Maieſty, but alſo <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned into fire euerlaſting, which was prepared for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 41.</note> 
               <hi>the Diuell and his angels,</hi> there to endure the wrath and vengeance of <hi>God</hi> for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>And leſt any one ſhould doubt, which was this Faith or Religion; he ſwore he would multiply it in men, <hi>as the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. <hi>Iſay</hi> 88. <hi>Iſay</hi> 54. <hi>Iſay</hi> 62.</note> 
               <hi>Starres of heauen;</hi> that remaining in all ages and times
<pb facs="tcp:16729:4"/> viſibly ſeene and profeſſed; none could or ſhould haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of doubting, which was this Faith or Religion, vnto the which he was ſo ſtraitly bound; vnleſſe he would wilfully be obſtinate and blinde: And yet notwithſtanding your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Miniſters, contrary to the oath of <hi>God,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of the penalty of eternall damnation impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on misbeleeuers, would perſwade vs that their Religion, which about threeſcore yeares agoe was inuented in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by Queene <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> (only to keepe your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Mother, and her iſſue from their lawfull right to the Crowne of <hi>England)</hi> is the Religion which was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Sauiour; and afflict vpon your ancient ſubiects, (who haue maintained your Progenitors in the ſtate of Kings and abſolute Monarkes, many hundred yeares) confiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of goods and lands, impriſonment, loſſe of liberty and life, and the benefit of all Ciuil and Humane lawes and conuerſation; for that we wil not beleeue them, to the loſſe of our owne ſoules, and in continuance of time, the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your Monarchie; according to the Prophecies, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>I will bleſſe them that bleſſe thee, and curſe them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 3.</note> 
               <hi>that curſe thee: In thee ſhall all the Kindreds of the earth be bleſſed. The Nation and the Kingdome that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 60. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not ſerue thee ſhall periſh.</hi> Which we haue ſeene ſo manifeſtly fulfilled in al ages &amp; times amongst Chriſtians, that hitherto neuer any Nation, People, or Countrey of Chriſtian men, did ſeparate it ſelfe by Schiſme from the Catholike Church, the ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> dilated ouer the world; but it was within few yeares conquered by barbarus people.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, we your ancient ſubiects, feareful leſt we ſhould be forſaken of <hi>God,</hi> and fal into theſe euils, and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous in any thing to offend your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> our deareſt Soueraigne; proſtrate at your feete, doe humbly offer vnto your <hi>Highneſſe;</hi> the grounds and foundations of our Faith and Religion; by which we proue that it is the ſame Faith
<pb facs="tcp:16729:4"/> and Religion, which was planted vpon earth by our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in which al the Kindreds of the earth were to be bleſſed: hoping therby to remoue away from your <hi>Majeſties</hi> minde, theſe ſiniſter falſe informations, which ſuch as neither wiſh well, either to your Perſon or State, more then may ſerue to the accompliſhing of their deſignes, daily publiſh in your preſence, viz. <hi>That we are wilfull diſloyall Subjects, who vnder pretext of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, pretend Rebellion. Ignorant blinde people, that haue nothing to ſay for the Religion we profeſſe. Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to your</hi> Maieſty <hi>and State, &amp;c.</hi> That your <hi>Majeſty</hi> being better informed; we alſo may taſte of the ſweetneſſe of your Gouernment, who are at al times, and in al things, as readie to obey and ſerue you, our dread Soueraigne, as our Aunceſtors haue ſerued and obeyed your Progeniters, Kings, and abſolute Monarkes of this Iland; or as the Catholike ſubiects of the <hi>Emperour,</hi> or of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Polonie,</hi> do ſerue their Soueraignes: And in teſtimony hereof, we offer to binde our ſelues, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to remaine loyal &amp; faithful Subiects vnto your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> your Heires, and lawful Succeſſours, by amoath; whereby we may not, in effect and deed, ſweare that <hi>God</hi> Almighty is forſworne, in violating his oath and promiſes, which he made to the Patriarks and Prophets, euery where ſpoken of in the Scriptures, to be fulfilled in that Faith, Seede and Religion, which was to be planted vpon earth by his only Son, our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> wel knoweth, that it is not yet much about threeſcore yeares, ſince theſe your Kingdomes of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> were Catholike, and the moſt of vs, together with our Aunceſtors, neuer were of any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <note place="margin">See this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> then this we now profeſſe, ſince our Conuerſion to Chriſtianity from Paganiſme: And if we ſhould now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it, for feare of the loſſe of temporall goods, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and hanging; and not out of information in beleefe,
<pb facs="tcp:16729:5"/> we ſhould be but Atheiſts, and be worthy to be hanged vp indeed, for diſſembling with men, and violating all obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, the meanes which <hi>God</hi> Almighty appointed his Officers to vſe in the conuerſion of Kingdomes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was, Humility, Patience, Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaying: <hi>Behold</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>I ſend you, as ſheepe in the middeſt of Wolues:</hi> he did not ſay, I ſend you as Wolues amongst ſheepe, to kill, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſpoyle, and deuoure thoſe vnto whom they were ſent. Againe he ſaid: <hi>They</hi> (to whom I ſend you) <hi>will deliuer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 17.</note> 
               <hi>you vp in Councels, and in their Synagogues they wil ſcourge you. And to Preſidents, and to Kings ſhall you be led for my ſake:</hi> He doth not ſay, you whom I ſend ſhall deliuer the people, whom you ought to conuert, into Councels, and put them in priſons, and leade them to Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and Tribunall ſeats, and make their Religion Fellony and Treaſon. Againe he ſaith: <hi>When yee enter into</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the houſe, ſalute it, ſaying, Peace be to this houſe:</hi> He doth not ſay, you ſhall ſend Purſuiuants to ranſacke and ſpoyle the houſe. Againe he ſaith: <hi>The good Paſtor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>his life for his ſheepe. The theefe commeth not but to ſteale, and kill, and deſtroy:</hi> He doth not ſay, the theefe giueth his life for his ſheepe; and the good Paſtor commeth not but to ſteale, kill and deſtroy.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſo much as is lawful for poore ſubiects, wee humbly beſeech your <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> that conuerting of vs by kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, impriſonments, confiſcation of goods, ranſacking and ſpoyling by Promoters and Purſuiuants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> laid aſide, (at which the Chriſtian world is ſcandalized) it would pleaſe your <hi>Majeſtie</hi> to giue order, that Diſputations, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and ſweet meanes may be vſed for the diſcuſſion of truth, according to the doctrine of our <hi>Sauiour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> which is <hi>Peaceable, modeſt ſuaſible, conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the good, full of mercie:</hi> and by thoſe meanes, if <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> 3. 17.</note> we ſhould be in error, your <hi>Majeſtie</hi> might eaſily gaine vs.
<pb facs="tcp:16729:5"/> And if your <hi>Majeſty</hi> be amiſſe, as <hi>errare facile eſt,</hi> wee may gaine your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and bring all things to his happie iſſue, that <hi>God</hi> Almightie may be glorified by the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſoules; and your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> may, to our great comfort, ſo raigne ouer vs vpon earth, that you may alſo raigne amongst vs in heauen, which with all my heart I deſire, and to that end proceed to ſet downe the grounds and foundations of our <hi>Catholike Faith</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> by way of an Appeale vnto your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> this being the beſt way, as your <hi>Majeſtie</hi> moſt graciouſly hath ſignified vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all your Subiect in your Speech in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> vpon the twentith of Iune, in the yeare of our Lord, 1616. in theſe words: <hi>Why ſhould you ſpare to complaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that being the high-way, and not go the other by-way, and back-way, in contempt of our authority.</hi> According to which ſpeech, worthy of a Royall King, with Saint <hi>PAVL</hi> in the like caſe of Religion, <hi>I appeale to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 25. 11.</note> 
               <hi>CAESAR,</hi> your <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> my dread and Supreameſt <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> as followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16729:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16729:6"/>
            <head>THAT OVR SAVIOVR PLANTED the Catholike Roman Faith.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is proued by the Scriptures, that the Catholike Roman Faith, is the Faith which was planted by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: and how it hath continued, and ſhall continue amongst the Romans, vntill the day of Iudgement.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, that the</hi> Romans <hi>receiued the Catholike Faith which our</hi> Sauiour <hi>planted: Saint</hi> Paul <hi>witneſſeth, ſaying,</hi> To all you that be at Rome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued <note place="margin">Rom: 1.</note> of God, called Saints, grace to you, and peace from God the Father, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Firſt truely I giue thankes to my God, through Ieſus Chriſt for all you: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your faith is publiſhed throughout the whole world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I deſire to ſee you, and to bee comforted in you, by the faith, which is mutually yours, and mine. <hi>Which deſire after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he obtained,</hi> And tarried <hi>(in Rome)</hi> full two yeares <note place="margin">Act. 28. 30.</note> in his hired lodging, and he receiued all that came vnto him, preaching the Kingdome of God, and teaching the things that concerne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, with all confidence, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prohibition. <hi>Whereby it is manifeſt that the</hi> Romans <hi>receiued the Catholike Faith, planted by our</hi> Sauiour, <hi>and that their faith was</hi> publiſhed throughout the whole <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> world, <hi>and was Catholike and Vniuerſall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, that the</hi> Romans <hi>were to continue in this their Catholike Faith, thus planted amongſt them, vntill the worlds end, is manifeſt by the Scripture, ſaying:</hi> I <note place="margin">Iſa. 66.</note> will ſend of them that ſhall be ſaued to the Gentiles, into the Sea, into Africa and Lydia, into Italy and Greece, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And they ſhall ſhew my glory to the Gentiles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16729:7"/> will take of them to be Prieſts and Leuites, ſaith our Lord. Becauſe as a new heauen, and a new earth, which I make to ſtand before me; ſaith our Lord: ſo ſhall your ſeed ſtand, and your name. And there ſhall be moneth after moneth, and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath after Sabbath. <hi>Againe, the Scriptures ſpeaking of the</hi> Romans, <hi>who at the comming of our</hi> Sauiour <hi>were the ſtrength, glory, and pride of the Gentiles; ſay,</hi> The ſtrength of the Gentiles ſhall come to thee. <hi>Againe,</hi> And <note place="margin">Iſay 60 5.</note> thy gates ſhall be open continually, day and night they ſhall not be ſhut, that the ſtrength of the Gentiles may be brought to thee. <hi>Againe,</hi> You ſhall eate the ſtrength of the Gentiles, and in their glory you ſhall be proud, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For as the Earth <note place="margin">Iſay 61. 6.</note> bringeth forth her Spring, and as the Garden ſhooteth forth her ſeed: ſo ſhall our Lord God make Iustice to ſpring forth, and praiſe before all the Gentiles. <hi>Againe,</hi> Thus ſaith our <note place="margin">Iſay 66. 12.</note> Lord, Behold I will decline vpon her, as it were a floud of peace, and as a torrent ouerflowing the glory of the Gentiles, <hi>(the</hi> Roman Empire, <hi>which at the birth of our</hi> Sauiour <hi>was the glory of the</hi> Gentiles) <hi>that it might be verified which was ſpoken by the other Prophets, ſaying,</hi> I will make <note place="margin">Gen. 12. 2.</note> thee into a great Nation, and I will bleſſe thee, and magnifie thy name, and thou ſhalt be bleſſed. <hi>Againe,</hi> I will put him, <note place="margin">Pſal. 88. 28.</note> the firſt begotten, high aboue the Kings of the earth: And I will keepe my mercy vnto him for euer, and my Teſtament faithfull vnto him, I will put his ſeed for euer and euer, and his throne as the dayes of heauen. <hi>Againe,</hi> Aske of me, and <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 8.</note> I will giue thee the Gentiles for thine inheritance, <hi>not the refuſe of the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles, but the</hi> Roman Empire, <hi>the</hi> ſtrength, glory <hi>and</hi> pride of the Gentiles, <hi>and not onely for a ſhort time.</hi> But as a new Heauen, &amp; a new Earth; which I make <note place="margin">Iſay 66.</note> to ſtand before me; ſo ſhall your ſeed ſtand, and your name, <hi>according to the words of the Prophet</hi> Iſay <hi>before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whereby it is ſufficiently manifeſt, that the</hi> Romant <hi>receiued the ſame Faith, they now profeſſe, from the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>and they from our</hi> Sauiour: <hi>and that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16729:7"/> Roman <hi>Faith, is the Faith which was planted vpon earth by our</hi> Sauiour, <hi>and hath continued, and ſhall continue Catholike, or vniuerſally publiſhed throughout the world, vntill the day of Iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is proued that the Catholike Roman faith was planted in this Iland of great Brittaine, by the Apoſtles, or Diſciples of our Lord, and hath continued heere euer ſince, without alteration or change, except in the keeping of Eaſter, and ſome ceremonies in Baptiſme, and that no other doctrine but it, can be taught for Chriſtian doctrine, without incurring the penaltie of</hi> Anathema, <hi>and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19.</note> going by his appointment to teach all Nations, to obſerue, and doe all things whatſoeuer hee had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them; came within ſo ſhort a time after the death of our <hi>Lord</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this our Iland of great <hi>Brittan,</hi> as that the <hi>Britaines,</hi> ancient inhabitants of this Iland; receiued their Faith and Religion from Saint <hi>Simon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Zelotes,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Saint <hi>Ioſeph of Aramathia,</hi> a Diſciple of our Lords, or from all, or ſome of them, as beſides theſe ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Theodoret de cur Graec. affect. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Dorotheus</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Tyre, in ſuo Synopſi Apoſtolorum; Ariſtobulus,</hi> in his Epiſtle which he writ to the Romans: <hi>Guildas, cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Nicephorus, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 40. doe affirme alſo theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Authors, <hi>Camden</hi> in his <hi>Britania,</hi> pag. 40. &amp; 52. and 157. <hi>Bale, Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. Doctor <hi>Caius de Antiq. Cantab. Harriſon</hi> in his Deſcription of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to <hi>Hollinſhead</hi> his great Chronicle of the laſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16729:8"/> edition, vol. 1. pag. 23. <hi>Clapham</hi> in his Soueraigne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt Schiſme, pag. 24. <hi>Fulke</hi> in his booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Heskins, Saunders,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 561. and in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of Purgatory, pag. 332. <hi>Godwin</hi> in his Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Biſhops, pag. 1. <hi>Barlow</hi> in defence of the Articles of the Proteſtant Religion, pag. 21. <hi>Mayſon</hi> in his booke of the Conſecration of Biſhops, &amp;c. That it might be verified which was ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I will ſend of them, that ſhall bee ſaued to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 66. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>the Gentiles, to the Ilands farre off, to them that haue not heard of me.</hi> Againe, <hi>The Ilands expect mee, and the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 6. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhips of the ſea in the beginning, that I may bring thy ſons from a farre,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Brittans,</hi> the ancient Inhabitants of this Iland, did perſeuere in this ſaid Chriſtian Faith and Religion, which they receiued from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or <hi>Diſciples,</hi> not onely theſe ancient Writers doe teſtifie euery one for his time, <hi>Tertullian, lib. contra Iudaeos. Origen in Ezechiel, hom.</hi> 4. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Emperour <hi>Iouinian. Theodoret hiſt. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. But alſo Proteſtants themſelues giue ample teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that the <hi>Britaines,</hi> who inhabited that part of the Iland, which is now called <hi>England,</hi> being deſtroyed, and their name extinct by the <hi>Pagan Saxons:</hi> yet the remnant of the <hi>Brittans,</hi> which remained in <hi>Wales,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Faith and Religion which they receiued from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> or <hi>Diſciples,</hi> euen vnto the comming of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> into this Iland, for to conuert the Engliſh Pagan Saxons, which was about the yeare of our <hi>Lord,</hi> 599. as <hi>Bale</hi> in his Pageant of Popes, where he ſaith, <hi>The Brittans being conuerted by</hi> Ioſeph <hi>of</hi> Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathia, <hi>held that faith at</hi> Auguſtines <hi>comming.</hi> And <hi>Fulke</hi> in his Anſwere to a Counterfeit Catholike, pag. 40. where hee ſaith, <hi>The</hi> Brittans <hi>before</hi> Auguſtines <hi>comming, continued in the Faith of Chriſt, euen from the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>times.</hi> FOX his Act. pag. 463. printed 1576.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16729:8"/> ſaith, <hi>The</hi> Brittaines <hi>after the receiuing of the Faith, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forſooke it, for any maner of falſe preaching of others.</hi> And <hi>Midleton</hi> in his <hi>Papiſto maſtix,</hi> pag. 202. proueth by the teſtimony of the ancient Fathers, in ſucceeding ages, that the <hi>Brittaines</hi> did not forſake the Faith, and Religion which they receiued from S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and Saint <hi>Simon Zelotes,</hi> and Saint <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Aramathia,</hi> but continued in it, with the Catholike Chriſtians in other parts of the world.</p>
               <p>That this Faith and Religion, which the ancient Brittaines receiued from the Apoſtles or Diſciples, and perſeuered in vntill the comming of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> into this Iland, did not differ from that Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> profeſſed, and planted in this Iland amongſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> except the keeping of Eaſter vpon a wrong Sunday, out of ignorance in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomie, and the accompliſhment of ſome myſteries vſed in Baptiſme: beſides the teſtimony of Saint <hi>Beda hiſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. theſe Proteſtant Authors do affirme, <hi>Francis Mayſon</hi> in his book of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration of the Biſhops of the Church of England, pag. 58. where he ſaith, that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid to the Brittaine Biſhops: <hi>If you will in theſe three things obey me, that is, in celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Eaſter in due time, in accompliſhing the myſteries of Baptiſme (by which we are borne to God) according to the maner of the holy Roman and Apoſtolicall Church: and laſt of all, in preaching with vs to this Engliſh Nation the word of our Lord: all your other ceremonies, faſhions and cuſtomes, though they be contrary to ours, we will willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer, and be content to beare with.</hi> And the like affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Hollinſhead,</hi> Vol. 1. pag. 103. <hi>Godwin</hi> in his Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Biſhops, pag. 6. And the Proteſtant Author of the Hiſtory of Great-Brittaine, printed 1606. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. page 133.</p>
               <p>Whereby it is manifeſt, that (the keeping of Eaſter vpon a wrong Sunday, and the accompliſhment of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16729:9"/> myſteries of Baptiſme excepted) Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the ancient Brittaines held, profeſſed, and taught, one and the ſame Faith and Religion, and planted it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Engliſh of this Iland, who then were Pagans.</p>
               <p>That the Faith and Religion which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> profeſſed, and planted amongſt the Pagan Engliſh of this Iland, was the ſame, which at this day the Roman Catholikes of this Iland doe profeſſe, not onely all Catholike Authors doe affirme, but alſo Proteſtant Writers doe confeſſe, as <hi>Iohn Bale, Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 73. where he ſaith, That King <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> an Engliſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan King, <hi>Firſt of all Engliſh men, receiued of</hi> Gregory <hi>the firſt, Biſhop of Rome, by</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>the opinions of the Roman Religion.</hi> And <hi>Cent.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. hee ſaith, That AVGVSTINE <hi>brought in</hi> (amongſt the Engliſh, who before were Pagans) <hi>Monkes, Altars Veſtments, Images, Maſſes, Chalices, Croſſe, Candleſtickes, Banners, holy</hi> (as they call them) <hi>Veſſels, holy water, and bookes of Roman cuſtome. Their chiefeſt ſtudies were about the oblation of Maſſes.</hi> Doctor <hi>Humfrey</hi> in his <hi>Ieſuitiſme,</hi> part. 2. pag. 5. and 627. affirmeth, That Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> and Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> profeſſed and taught Maſſe, Purgatory, Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holeſome Hoaſt, prayer for the dead, Relikes, Tranſubſtantiation, hallowing of Churches, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, Monkiſh life, Papacie, and the reſt of the caos of Popiſh ſuperſtition, as he calleth it. <hi>And theſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>did</hi> AVGVSTINE, <hi>a great Monk taught by</hi> GRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GORY, <hi>a Monke) bring to the Engliſh,</hi> who before were Pagan. <hi>Aſcham</hi> in his Apologie, <hi>pro Caena Domini, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Miſſam,</hi> pag. 33. affirmeth, That <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was <hi>The eſtabliſher of all Popiſh doctrine.</hi> HARRISON in his laſt edition of his Deſcription of Brittanie, Vol. 1. pag. 27. ſaith, That <hi>Auguſtine</hi> brought in Poperie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Engliſh Saxons, who then were Pagan. And the like affirmeth <hi>Oſiander</hi> in his <hi>Epitom. hiſt. Eccl.</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16729:9"/> 
                  <hi>Cent.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 289. The <hi>Century Writers</hi> in the 6. Cent. chap. 10. col. 748. and other Proteſtants ſet downe more at large in the Proteſtants <hi>Apologie</hi> for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing that the Brittaines (the keeping of Eaſter vpon a wrong Sunday, &amp; the accompliſhment of the myſteries vſed in Baptiſme excepted) were all of one Faith and Religion with Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was in Faith and Religion a Roman Catholike, or Papiſt: we rightly inferre, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour was Author of that Faith and Religion, which Proteſtants doe call Papiſtrie: ſince that the Brittans receiued it, as is before ſaid, from the Apoſtles or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, and they from our Lord, and perſeuered in it with Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> and Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and the reſt of the Chriſtian world, without any alteration or change, ſauing ſome myſteries vſed in Baptiſme, and the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Eaſter vpon a wrong Sunday. In all things elſe they were ſo agreeable to the Faith and Religion, which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> held and taught; that theſe two things reformed, he deſired their helpe and aſſiſtance in the conuerſion of the Pagan Engliſh Nation, by preaching vnto them the Word of God, which hee neither could, nor would haue done, had they not both (theſe two things excepted) agreed in one, in al points of Faith and Religion: neither did S. <hi>Auſten</hi> labour to teach, or reforme the Brittaines in any thing elſe: and ſeeing in theſe two things (which to Proteſtants ſeeme of little moment) Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> made ſo great difficultie, that hee would not receiue them into the Communion of the Catholike Roman Church, vntill they condeſcended to reforme them: far greater diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie would he haue made in receiuing them, if they had held any point of Proteſtantiſme, and had denied the Maſſe, prayer for the dead, worſhip of Images, and eſteemed him an Antichriſtian man, or Idolater, &amp;c.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16729:10"/> Neither would he (though they ſhould haue offered themſelues) haue admitted them to preach, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict, and defame him amongſt the Engliſh Pagans, or Gentiles, vnto whom hee was ſent as an Apoſtle: much leſſe would he haue required their ayde and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in preaching vnto them, if they had accuſed him, as Proteſtants do now, of Idolatry, Antichriſtian doctrine, and to haue been ſonne of the Whore of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That the Catholike Roman Faith, which Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> planted amongſt the Engliſh Saxons, is at this day, and in all ages and times, ſince the ſaid planting hath been confeſſed, by ſome knowne Engliſh inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in this Iland, all our Writers, Chronicles, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Monuments, Lawes in ancient time made in fauour of it, Statutes of late yeeres made to ſuppreſſe it, the death of many for it, and the priſons full of ſuch as at this inſtant doe profeſſe it, giue ample teſtimony: and if any require further proofe, I referre him to a booke intituled <hi>The prudentiall Ballance of Religion,</hi> which treateth hereof at large.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I conclude, that our Sauiour was Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Catholike Roman Faith, and that (the keeping of Eaſter vpon a wrong Sunday, and ſome myſteries vſed in Baptiſme excepted) it hath in al ages and times, ſince the plantation thereof by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles or Diſciples, continued in this Iland; and that no man can or may preach, or teach any doctrine for Chriſtian doctrine, but the Catholike Roman Faith, vnder paine of <hi>Anathema,</hi> &amp;c. according to the words of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Although we, or an Angell from</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galath.</hi> 1. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>heauen Euangelize to you, beſides that we haue Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to you, be he</hi> Anathema: <hi>as wee haue ſaid before, ſo now we ſay againe; If any Euangelize to you, beſides that which you haue receiued, be he</hi> Anathema, that is, ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from <hi>God,</hi> according to the words of our <hi>Sauiour</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16729:10"/> ſaying, <hi>Depart from mee yee accurſed into euerlaſting</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24: 41.</note> 
                  <hi>fire, which was prepared for the Diuell and his angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So I appeale to your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> well pleaſed, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the wrong and iniuſtice, your Proteſtant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters doe vnto vs Catholikes, your ancient ſubiects, in perſecuting vs, for profeſſing that Faith and Religion, which was planted vpon earth by our Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, and euen from the Apoſtles times vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day, hath continued in this Iland: and humbly beſeech your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> that you would not thinke vs diſloyal or vnfaithfull to your Perſon or State, for that we will not become <hi>Anathemaes</hi> from <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the difference which was betweene the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Brittans and Saint AVGVSTINE, about the time of the keeping of Eaſter, it is manifeſt by Saint <hi>Beda, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. that the Brittans fell into this error, for want of skill in Aſtronomie, <hi>For they knew</hi> (ſaith Saint BEDA) <hi>as Chriſten men doe, that the reſurrection of our Lord ought alwayes to be celebrated on Sunday. But as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wilfred in S.</hi> Beda, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>ignorant men</hi> (in Aſtrologie) <hi>they had not learned when that Sunday ſhould come.</hi> That the Brittans fell into this error, after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> his time, is manifeſt by <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius,</hi> who, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de vita Conſtantini, cap.</hi> 8. affirmeth, that the ſame keeping of Eaſter was obſerued <hi>in the Citie of Rome, in Italy, Africke, Aegypt, Spaine, France, Britanie, Lybia, and all Greece, in the Dioceſſe of Aſia, and Pontus, and finally in Cicilia, with one vniforme conſent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16729:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is briefely proued by the generall conſent of all knowne Christian people, who liued in all ages and times, betweene the death of the Apoſtles, and riſing of</hi> Luther, <hi>that our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt was Author of the Catholike Roman Faith, which Proteſtants call Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtrie, knowne Heretikes on both parties only excepted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST. Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe, <hi>That the true Church</hi> (ſo they call their Church) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed preſently after the Apoſtles times.</hi> So <hi>Fulke</hi> in his anſwere to a Counterfeit Catholike, page 35. <hi>Sebaſtianus Franciſcus,</hi> in his Epiſtle <hi>de abrogandis ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis eccleſiaſticis,</hi> affirmeth, That <hi>for theſe fourteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, the Church</hi> (of Proteſtants) <hi>hath been no where externall and viſible.</hi> Peter Martyr <hi>de Votis,</hi> page 477. ſaith, <hi>That errours</hi> (ſo they call our Catholike Faith) <hi>did begin immediatly after the Apostles times.</hi> And page 476. he ſaith, <hi>That preſently after their age, men began to decline from the word of God:</hi> ſo they eſteeme their Proteſtantiſme. The Proteſtant Author of the booke intituled <hi>Antichriſtus ſiue Pronoſtica finis mundi,</hi> page 13. affirmeth; <hi>That from the Apoſtles times, till</hi> Luther, <hi>the Gospell</hi> (of Proteſtants) <hi>had neuer open paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</hi> Melancthon <hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor. cap.</hi> 3. affirmeth, <hi>Thet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently from the beginning of the Church, the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers obſcured the doctrine, concerning the iuſtification of Faith, encreaſed Ceremonies, and deuiſed peculiar Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Peter Martyr de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>otis,</hi> page 476. ſaith: <hi>As long as wee ſhall inſiſt vpon Councels and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we ſhall be alwayes in the ſame errors.</hi> And <hi>Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> in his Controu. 2. queſt. 5. page 299. <hi>de Eccleſia,</hi> ſaith: BELLARMINE <hi>doth bring foorth certaine te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16729:11"/> 
                  <hi>out of</hi> Caluin, <hi>and the Centurie Writers, who haue noted certaine errors of the ancient Fathers, which they hold common with Papiſts, that is to ſay, of</hi> Free-will, <hi>of</hi> Merit, <hi>of the</hi> Limbe, <hi>of</hi> Inuocation of Saints, <hi>of the</hi> Vnmaried life of Biſhops, <hi>of</hi> Iuſtification, <hi>&amp;c. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that it is true, which</hi> Caluin <hi>and the</hi> Centuries <hi>haue written, that in many things the ancient Church hath erred, as of the</hi> Limbe, <hi>of</hi> Free-will, <hi>of the</hi> Merit of Workes, <hi>and in other things which are aboue rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> WHITGIFT in his Defence to the Anſwere to the <hi>Admonition,</hi> page 473. ſaith: <hi>How greatly were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Biſhops, and learned Writers of the Greeke Church, and Latine alſo, for the moſt part ſpotted with doctrine of</hi> Free-will, <hi>of</hi> Merits, <hi>of</hi> Inuocation of Saints, <hi>and ſuch like?</hi> And page 473. he ſaith; <hi>Surely you are not able to reckon in any age, ſince the Apoſtles times, any company of Biſhops, that taught and held ſo ſound doctrine in all points, as the Biſhops of</hi> England <hi>doe at this day.</hi> Whereupon, <hi>Luther</hi> in his booke <hi>De ſeruo arbitrio, tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Wittenb.</hi> 1551. affirmeth the Fathers to haue been blinde and moſt ignorant in the Scriptures, to haue erred al the time of their liues (from his doctrine) and that vnleſſe they were amended before their deathes, they were neither Saints, nor pertaining to the Church (of Proteſtants). And in his <hi>Colloquijs men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalibus,</hi> he ſaith: <hi>In the Writings of</hi> Hierome, <hi>there is not a word of true faith in Chriſt, and ſound religion.</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian <hi>is very ſuperſtitious. I hold</hi> Origen <hi>long ſince ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed. Of</hi> Chryſoſtome <hi>I make no account.</hi> Baſil <hi>is of no worth, he is wholly a Monke.</hi> Cyprian <hi>is a weake Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. The Apologie of</hi> Philip Melancthon <hi>doth farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell all the Doctors of the Church, and exceede euen</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine <hi>himſelfe.</hi> POMERAN, a Proteſtant vpon <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> ſaith: <hi>Our Fathers, whether holy, or not holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I eſteeme nothing, they haue been blinded with the Spirit of</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16729:12"/> Montanus, <hi>by humane traditions, and doctrine of diuels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They doe not teach purely of</hi> Iuſtification. <hi>Beza</hi> in his Preface vpon the New Teſtament, Dedicated to the Prince of <hi>Condy,</hi> printed 1587. affirmeth; <hi>That euen in the beſt times, the ambition, ignorance, and lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Biſhops was ſuch, that the very blinde may eaſily perceiue, how Satan was Preſident in their aſſemblies or Councels,</hi> becauſe they taught oppoſite doctrine to the doctrine of the Proteſtants of this age. Whereupon <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Expoſition of the Creede, page 400. in behalfe of himſelfe and all Proteſtants, ſaith, <hi>Wee ſay that before the dayes of</hi> Luther, <hi>for the ſpace of many hundred yeares, an vniuerſall Apoſtaſie</hi> (from Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, as hee meaneth) <hi>ouer-ſpread the whole face of the earth, and that our Church</hi> (of Proteſtants) <hi>was not viſible to the world.</hi> And many more Proteſtants confeſſe that the Faith or doctrine, which Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants now teach and profeſſe, hath been no where viſibly knowne, publiſhed, or preached, ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times vntil <hi>Luther,</hi> as is ſet down more at large in the Proteſtants Apologie for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>And it is of it ſelfe ſo manifeſt, that no Proteſtant hath hitherto bin able to aſſigne in the time betweene the death of the Apoſtles, and riſing of <hi>Luther,</hi> one onely Proteſtant Miniſter, Doctor, Writer or Teacher, that held, profeſſed, or taught the doctrine which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants doe now hold and teach.</p>
               <p>Whereby it is manifeſt, that in all that time, which is about the ſpace of one thouſand foure hundred yeares, there were no knowne Proteſtants, but all knowne Chriſtians, who liued within the compaſſe of theſe yeares, were either Roman Catholikes, or repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Heretikes by both parties. Whereupon we right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inferre, that all knowne Chriſtian men, who liued in all ages ſince the time of the Apoſtles, vntill the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Luther</hi> (knowne Heretikes, and ſo reputed by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16729:12"/> both partie onely excepted) doe teſtifie that our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt was Author of the Catholike Romaine Faith; euery Chriſtian beleeuing that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt was the Author of this Religion, and Planter thereof vpon earth.</p>
               <p>Now that there were knowne Roman Catholikes, liuing, and being, during theſe fourteene hundred yeares; Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe. <hi>Fulke</hi> in his Treatiſe againſt <hi>Stapleton,</hi> page 25. affirmeth: <hi>Some Proteſtants haue written, that the Pope hath blinded the world theſe many hundred yeares; ſome ſay a thouſand, ſome one thouſand two hundred, ſome nine hundred.</hi> And the ſame Proteſtant in his retentiue Motiues, pag. 248. ſpeaking of <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> Biſhops of Rome, the firſt of them liuing about the yeare of our Lord, 440. and the ſecond of them about 590. ſaith: <hi>The myſtery of iniquitie</hi> (ſo he calleth the Pope and our Catholike Faith) <hi>wrought in the Sea of Rome, neare fiue or ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares before them.</hi> MIDLETON in his <hi>Papiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix,</hi> page 193. affirmeth, ſaying: <hi>Wee are ſure that the myſterie of iniquitie</hi> (ſo he pleaſeth to call the Pope, and our Catholike Faith) <hi>did worke in</hi> Pauls <hi>time, and fell not a ſleepe as ſoone as</hi> Paul <hi>was dead,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no maruell though peruſing Councels, Fathers and Stories, from the Apoſtles forward, wee finde the print of the Popes feete.</hi> SEBASTIAN FRANCVS, in his Epiſtle <hi>De abrogandis Statutis eccleſiaſticis,</hi> affirmeth: <hi>That for certaine through the worke of Antichriſt</hi> (ſo he calleth the Pope, and our Catholike Faith) <hi>the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church</hi> (of Proteſtants) <hi>together with the Faith and Sacraments vaniſhed away preſently after the Apoſtles departure.</hi> So potent were the Pope and Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, euen in the Apoſtles times, that preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apoſtles departure, they were able to make the externall Church of Proteſtants, together with the Faith and Sacraments of Proteſtants vaniſhed away,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16729:13"/> as this Proteſtant affirmeth. <hi>Brokard</hi> in his Treatiſe vpon the Reuelations, pag. 110. affirmeth, That <hi>the Church</hi> (of Proteſtants) <hi>was troden downe, and oppreſſed by the Papacie, euen from</hi> Sylueſters <hi>time vnto theſe times.</hi> Which he there, and page 123. accounteth to haue been for the ſpace of 1260. yeares. <hi>Napper</hi> in his Treatiſe vpon the Reuelations, pag. 68. ſaith: <hi>Betweene the yeare of Chriſt,</hi> 300. <hi>and</hi> 316. <hi>the Antichriſtian and Papiſticall raigne began raigning vniuerſally, and without any debatable contradiction,</hi> 1260. <hi>yeares;</hi> and pag. 145. he ſaith, <hi>euen</hi> 1260. <hi>yeares the Pope and his Cleargie hath poſſeſſed the outward viſible Church of Chriſtians.</hi> Yet the Pope and his Cleargie could not come to raigne vniuerſally, and without any debatable contradiction vpon a ſudden, as wee ſee by experience in Proteſtant Miniſters, who haue beene now about an hundred yeares, and yet doe not reigne, or poſſeſſe their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in any one Countrey: without ſome oppoſition, whereby it is manifeſt, that the Pope and his Cleargie were many hundred yeares, before they could obtaine to reigne vniuerſally without any debatable contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Downham</hi> in his Treatiſe of Antichriſt, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 25. affirmeth; That <hi>the generall defection of the viſible Church, foretold in the ſecond of the Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> (which hee eſteemeth to haue beene wrought by the Pope and Roman Catholikes) <hi>began to worke in the Apoſtles times. Caelus ſecundus Curio,</hi> in his booke <hi>De amplitudine Regni Dei, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 43. ſaith; <hi>Are we ignorant in how great darkeneſſe, blindneſſe, and ignorance</hi> (ſo he calleth our Catholike Faith) <hi>the world hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued almoſt from the Apoſtles age, to theſe very times, in which aboue all expectation our Lord began to manifeſt himſelfe.</hi> And <hi>Perkins</hi> vpon the Creed, page 307. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth; <hi>That during the ſpace of nine hundred yeares, the Popiſh hereſie</hi> (ſo he pleaſeth to call the Catholike
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16729:13"/> Roman Faith) <hi>hath ſpread it ſelfe ouer the whole earth:</hi> whereby appeareth that it was fiue or ſixe hundred yeares before; ſince it could not ſpread it ſelfe of a ſudden ouer the whole earth. And by theſe confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Proteſtants themſelues, and by many more, ſet downe in the Proteſtants Apologie, it is manifeſt that the Catholike Roman Faith did begin euen in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, and hath raigned vniuerſally ouer the viſible Church of Chriſtians 1260. yeares, if wee will beleeue the confeſſion of our Aduerſaries themſelues.</p>
               <p>So dread <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> if the teſtimonies of all known Chriſtian men, who liued in all ages and times, from the Apoſtles times, vntill the riſing of <hi>Luther,</hi> may find grace and credit with your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> they all (knowne Heretikes, and ſo reputed by both parties onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) doe witneſſe, that our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith; for that they all beleeued and eſteemed our Lord to be Author of that Religion, they themſelues profeſſed.</p>
               <p>And this were ſufficient to ſhew vnto your moſt excellent <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> that the Sonne of God was Author of the Catholike Roman Faith: but becauſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miniſters do ſo often bragge, that the Scriptures, or written Word of God doth make for them: I will further examine the Scriptures, to ſee what they ſay of the Religion which was to be planted by our Sauiour, and wil begin with the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, according to the directions of our Lord, ſaying; <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> (the olde Teſtament, for as then no part of the New <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 39.</note> was written) <hi>for you thinke by them to haue life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and the ſame are they that giue teſtimony of me:</hi> and after deſcend downe vnto the New, and ſo prooue by the generall conſent of the whole Scriptures, that our Sauiour was Author of the Catholike Roman Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16729:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is proued by the testimony of</hi> Moyſes <hi>and the Patriarkes, that our Sauiour was Author of the Catholike Roman Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O diſcerne the true <hi>Prophet</hi> from the falſe, and to diſcerne the word of God from the words of arrogant men; God Almightie gaue vs this rule, ſaying: <hi>If in ſecret cogitation thou anſwere. How</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall I vnderſtand the word that our Lord ſpake not? This ſigne thou ſhalt haue: that which the ſame Prophet foretelleth in the name of the Lord, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to paſſe, that our Lord hath not ſpoken. But by the arrogancie of his minde, the Prophet hath forged it. And the Prophet, that being depraued with arrogancie,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>will ſpeake in my name the things that I did not command him to ſay, ſhall be ſlaine.</hi> Whereupon our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>All things muſt needs bee fulfilled, which are written in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Law of</hi> Moyſes, <hi>and the Prophets, and Pſalmes of mee,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the Prophets, ſhould haue been falſe Prophets, and our Sauiour none of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> but a ſeducer and deceiuer, and the <hi>God</hi> of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a falſe God. So ſuppoſing that our Sauiour was the <hi>Meſſias</hi> promiſed to be ſent, for the redemption of mankinde, and that the Prophets of both Teſtaments were true Prophets, and not guiltie of death, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied things which muſt be infallibly fulfilled. We will ſeeke out what they ſay of the Seed, Faith, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Goſpell, which was to be planted by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vpon earth.</p>
               <p>And to let paſſe other promiſes and prophecies written by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> we will begin with that great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16729:14"/> and oath made by God to ABRAHAM, <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all that beleeue:</hi> Whereupon is grounded and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11.</note> founded the ſucceſſion of the Church in all ages; the oath of God being the higheſt act, that can bee made in heauen or in earth, in confirmation of a truth, it cannot bee contradicted without great impietie; or denied to be fulfilled, without making the God of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> our Lord, to bee forſworne, and a falſe God, which is the higheſt kinde of vntruth; oppoſite to the greateſt truth that can be giuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> going to ſacrifice his only begotten ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> according as God had commanded him; ſo greatly pleaſed his diuine Maieſtie in that act of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, that he confirmed his former promiſe made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him <hi>(that he ſhould be heire of the world)</hi> by an oath, ſaying; <hi>By my owne ſelfe haue I ſworne, ſaith the Lord,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 3. and 15. 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe thou haſt done this thing, and haſt not ſpared thy onely begotten ſonne for my ſake. I will bleſſe thee, and I will multiply thy ſeede as the ſtarres of heauen, and as the ſand that is by the ſea-ſhore, thy ſeede ſhall poſſeſſe the gates of his enemies, and in thy ſeede ſhall be bleſſed all the Nations of the earth, becauſe thou haſt obeyed my voyce. He ſaith not</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) and to ſeeds, as in many;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galath.</hi> 3. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>but as in one, and to thy ſeede, which is Chriſt.</hi> That in Chriſt <hi>Ieſus,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> not the Nation of the Iewes, or Brittans onely, but all the Nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, and become children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſonnes, and ſeede of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus, borne againe</hi> (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) <hi>not of corruptible ſeed, but incorruptible by the word of God.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23.</note> Whereupon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Corinthians, In</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt Ieſus, by the Goſpell, I begate you.</hi> And to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> he ſaith, That <hi>the Gentiles are coheires, and of the ſame body, and partakers of his promiſe by the Goſpel.</hi> And ſo ſaith, That <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galath.</hi> 5. 14.</note>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16729:15"/> 
                  <hi>curſe of the Law, that on the Gentiles the bleſſing of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>might be made in Chriſt Ieſus, that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the promiſe. The Scriptures foreſeeing that God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galath.</hi> 3. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>the Gentiles by Faith, ſhewed vnto</hi> Abraham <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that in thee ſhall all Nations be bleſſed.</hi> Not for a day, or a yeare, but for euer, according to the words of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> ſaying: <hi>He hath receiued Iſrael his childe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>being mindfull of his mercy: As he ſpake to our Fathers, to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his ſeed for euer.</hi> So likewiſe God ſaid to ABRAHAM, SARA <hi>thy wife ſhall beare thee a ſon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and thou ſhalt call his name</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and I will eſtabliſh my couenant to him, for a perpetuall couenant, and to his ſeed after him.</hi> Whereby wee ſee that this oath of God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> is to bee fulfilled in and vpon Chriſtians, profeſſing the Faith and Goſpell planted by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and that thoſe Chriſtians, vpon whom this oath can, or may be fulfilled, are the ſeede of our Sauiour, and the children of his Kingdome, and heires of the Promiſes, &amp; none elſe, vnleſſe we will make God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie forſworne, which is too great impietie, and a vanitie for any man to acknowledge him for a God, whom he profeſſeth in deeds to be a violater of oathes and promiſes. So it reſteth to examine, whether this oath of God be verified vpon Roman Catholikes, or vpon Proteſtants: that we may clearely ſee which of them are true Chriſtians, and heires of the Promiſes, and ſeed of our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>And as for Proteſtants, they themſelues confeſſe, that their Faith and Religion, which they now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, hath been ſo farre off from being multiplied as the Starres of heauen, and as the ſand that is by the ſea ſhore, that preſently after the Apoſtles times it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came no where externall or viſible; as we haue ſhewed in the precedent Chapter: And it is of it ſelfe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that Proteſtants are not able, from the time
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16729:15"/> of the Apoſtles, vntill the riſing of <hi>Luther,</hi> which is during the ſpace of fourteene hundred years or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, to aſſigne one knowne man of the Religion they now profeſſe. If this oath be made to Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, where is the ſeede of Proteſtants <hi>multiplied as the Starres of heauen, and as the ſand that is by the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore?</hi> Seeing that for many hundred yeares, neuer a Proteſtant Starre appeared. And if this oath was made to Proteſtants, That <hi>they ſhould poſſeſſe the gates of their enemies, and that in their ſeed, all the Nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed: As he ſpake to</hi> Abraham, <hi>and his ſeede</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>for euer.</hi> How commeth it to paſſe, that preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apoſtles times, Proteſtants were ſo ouercome by Roman Catholikes, that from that time vntill <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> they haue been no where viſibly knowne, but ſo latent and inuiſible, as for all that ſpace they cannot produce one Proteſtant Miniſter or Doctour, who taught or maintained the doctrine they now teach?</p>
               <p>If it be true that the God of the Proteſtants hath made theſe promiſes, and this oath to them, it muſt needs be, that he is a very wretched vnfaithfull God, that hath for fourteene hundred, or fifteene hundred yeares together violated his oath and promiſes.</p>
               <p>And I appeale to your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> well pleaſed to conſider how great injuſtice it is, to haue your ancient Subjects ſpoyled of their Lands, Goods, Libertie and Life, and be condemned as Fellons and Traytors, for that they wil not beleeue in ſuch a prejured God. And how happie a thing it is to be a Roman Catholike, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this oath of God is ſo manifeſtly fulfilled in them, that (as it is ſet downe in the laſt Chapter) euen our Aduerſaries themſelues confeſſe, for twelue hundred ceares together they haue bin dilated ouer the world, and poſſeſſed the gates of their enemies, and bleſſed all the Chriſtian Families of the earth with temporall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16729:16"/> and ſpirituall birth, by regeneration in Baptiſme, and education, &amp;c. <hi>Theſe are the ſeed of</hi> Abraham <hi>his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.</note> 
                  <hi>the children of</hi> Iacob <hi>his elect, he is the Lord our God, in all the earth are his iudgements, he hath bin mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for euer of his Testament, of the Word which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vnto thouſand generations. Our Lord is not as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut</hi> 32. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>their Gods: our enemies alſo are Iudges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may pleaſe your <hi>Maieſty</hi> to obſerue the notes and markes of our Catholike Romane Church, and Faith, heere ſet downe in this oath of God to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> viz. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Vniuerſality,</hi> and <hi>Succeſſion.</hi> The Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is promiſed in theſe words, <hi>Thy ſeed,</hi> not diuers ſeeds, that there might bee as many ſects, as men, as ſome <hi>Elizabethians,</hi> ſome <hi>Lutherans,</hi> ſome <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> ſome <hi>Huſſites,</hi> ſome <hi>Anabaptiſtes,</hi> ſome <hi>Armenians,</hi> ſome <hi>Gomariſtes,</hi> ſome <hi>Traſquits;</hi> all differing in Faith and Religion: but one ſeede, Faith, or Word of God planted in the hearts of men, by the preaching of our Lord, as witneſſeth our Sauiour, expounding the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Cockle of the field, ſaid to his Diſciples: <hi>He that ſoweth good ſeed, is the Sonne of man.</hi> Againe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>The good ſeed, thoſe are the children of the Kingdome.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 38.</note> Againe. <hi>O Father, the words which thou gaueſt me, I</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Io.</hi> 17. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>haue giuen them: and they haue receiued, and knoweth in very deed, that I came forth from thee, and haue beleeued that thou diddeſt ſend me,</hi> to fulfill the promiſes made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Patriarkes and Prophets.</p>
               <p>The ſecond marke is <hi>Catholike</hi> or Vniuerſall, heere promiſed in theſe words: <hi>And I will multiply thy ſeed as the Starres of heauen:</hi> which doe manifeſtly appeare and ſhine in all Countries. <hi>And God brought</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>forth abroad, and ſaid to him: Looke vp to heauen, and number the Starres if thou canſt. And he ſaid to him, ſo ſhall thy ſeed be,</hi> as the Starres of heauen, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in all Countries; not onely in <hi>Brittanie, France,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16729:16"/> or in <hi>Germany,</hi> but in all Nations, according to the oath of God, ſaying: <hi>In thy ſeed ſhall be bleſſed all the Nations of the earth.</hi> Whereupon our Sauiour ſaid; <hi>He that ſoweth good ſeed, is the Sonne of Man,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>the field is the world.</hi> Againe, <hi>You are the light of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>world.</hi> Againe, <hi>Teach yee all Nations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The third marke is <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> which is promiſed in theſe words: <hi>Thy ſeed ſhall poſſeſſe the gates of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>As he ſpake to our Fathers, to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeed for euer:</hi> not that the Succeſſion ſhould decay, or become inuiſible; that there ſhould neede new miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but that it ſhould continue vntill the worlds end; according to the words of our Sauiour, ſaying: <hi>I haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>appointed you, that you go and bring fruit, and your fruit abide.</hi> Againe, <hi>And this Gospell of the Kingdome ſhall be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>preached in al Nations, and then ſhal come the conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the world. Againe, <hi>The gates of hell ſhall not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>preuaile againſt it,</hi> &amp;c. And the like three markes, or notes of the Church, which was to be planted by our Sauiour, your <hi>Maieſty</hi> may obſerue to be ſet downe almoſt in euery Prophecie; though I omit to ſpeake more of them for breuities ſake.</p>
               <p>Secondly, God Almightie promiſed to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>I will performe the oath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which I ſware vnto</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.</note> 
                  <hi>thy father, and I will multiply thy ſeed as the Starres of heauen; and in thy ſeed ſhall be bleſſed all the Nations of the earth, becauſe</hi> Abraham <hi>obeyed my voice, and kept my precepts and Commandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, hee promiſed to <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Thy ſeed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall be as the duſt of the earth, thou ſhalt be dilated to the Weſt, and to the Eaſt, and to the North, and to the South, and in thee, and thy ſeed, all the Families of the earth ſhal be bleſſed, and I will be thy keeper whereſoeuer thou ſhalt go, and I will bring thee againe into this Land, neither wil I forſake thee, vntill I haue performed whatſoeuer I haue</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16729:17"/> 
                  <hi>ſpoken.</hi> Which Prophecies we ſee haue been manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfilled in our Catholike Roman Faith, which hath been vniuerſally and ſucceſſiuely dilated ouer all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, according to theſe Prophecies, as we haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the former Chapters: and can no way be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vpon Proteſtantiſme, ſince it decayed preſently after the Apoſtles times; and for a thouſand and foure hundred yeares together, was neuer knowne to haue been taught or practiſed, and now is but ſcattered in diuers corners of the earth, diuided into many ſects, teaching oppoſite doctrine in matters of Faith, and heere we ſeeke for one Faith, or ſeed dilated ouer the world.</p>
               <p>God Almightie heere ſaith; <hi>I will performe the oath which I ſware to</hi> Abraham, <hi>neither will I forſake thee, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I haue performed whatſoeuer I haue ſpoken.</hi> And I appeale to your <hi>Maieſty</hi> wel pleaſed to conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee more conuenient to beleeue the words of God, when hee ſaith, hee will performe his oath and promiſes, then the words of Proteſtant Miniſters, who affirme that the ſeede of Chriſt hath failed, and now after a thouſand and fiue hundred yeares, they are ſent to plant it, in corners of the earth. <hi>What is found more madde,</hi> (ſaith Saint AVGVSTINE) <hi>then this folly, or</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>August. cont. epiſt. Parmenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>rather frenzie? In ſo many Nations of the world, and for the moſt part God hath fulfilled, and doth yet fulfill, vntill it come vnto all, which he hath promiſed; who ſaid,</hi> I will not leaue thee, vntill I doe theſe things, which I haue ſpoken vnto thee: <hi>And now theſe</hi> (Proteſtants) <hi>doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſuch as tell them, that it is not fulfilled what God promiſed; and that therefore the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>which is Chriſt, to haue decayed in thoſe parts of the earth, in which it was planted; and that the promiſes of God are voide, becauſe they are not admitted into their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, amongst whom it is fulfilled.</hi> Thus Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16729:17"/>
               <p> So If the oath of God, or the Promiſes made to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> written by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> may finde grace and credit with your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by their teſtimonies, that our Sauiour was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Catholike Romane Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the teſtimony of the Prophet</hi> DAVID, <hi>and the Pſalmes, our Sauiour was Author of the Catholike Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Sauiour ſaith, That <hi>all things muſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>needs be fulfilled which is written in the Pſalmes of him.</hi> So we will examine what the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> ſay of our Sauiour and his ſeede, the Chriſtians, that wee may ſee, whether the Prophecies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein be verified vpon Romane Catholikes, or vpon Proteſtants; it being now a thouſand and ſix hundred yeares ſince the Natiuitie of our Sauiour; thoſe muſt needs be his ſeed, and true Chriſtians, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom they are verified, ſeeing that it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>for God to lye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, the Pſalmes ſay; <hi>Thou art my Sonne, this day haue I begotten thee: Aske of me, and I will giue thee the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Gentiles for thine inheritance, and thy poſſeſſion, the ends of the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>All the ends of the earth ſhal remember,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>and be conuerted to our Lord: and all the Families of the Gentiles ſhall adore in his fight: Becauſe the Kingdome is our Lords, and he ſhall haue dominion ouer the Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>For thy fathers there are borne ſons to thee,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.</note> 
                  <hi>thou ſhalt make them Princes ouer all the earth, they ſhall</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16729:18"/> 
                  <hi>be mindefull of thy name in all generation, and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for euer, and for euermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>The God of gods, our Lord hath ſpoken, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>hath called the earth, from the riſing of the Sinne, vnto the going downe thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, <hi>Their ſound is gone into all the earth, and their</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>words into the ends of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, <hi>He ſhall deſcend as raine vpon a fleece of wooll,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and as the drops diſtilling vpon the earth. In his dayes ſhal ariſe Iuſtice and abundance of peace, ſo long as the Moone endureth. And he ſhall rule from ſea to ſea, and from the riuer vnto the end of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seuenthly, <hi>I will put him, the firſt begotten, higher</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>then the Kings of the earth. I will keepe my mercies vnto him for euer, and my Teſtament faithfull to him. I will put his ſeed for euer and euer, and his Throne as the dayes of heauen. But if his children ſhall forſake my Law, and keepe not my Commandements, I will viſite their iniquitie with a rod, and their ſinnes with ſtripes; but my mercy I will not take away from him, neither will I hurt in my truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And many more the like Prophecies of the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Gentiles, and propagation of the Faith, or ſeede of our Sauiour ouer the world for euer; which cannot bee verified vpon Proteſtants, or Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, who haue beene ſo farre off from hauing the Gentiles for their inheritance, and their Poſſeſſions vnto the ends of the earth, or conuerting all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the Gentiles, or from hauing abundance of peace, as long as the Moone endureth, or from hauing their ſeed to endure for euer, and their throne as the dayes of heauen: that in all the time which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the death of the Apoſtles, and the rebellion of <hi>Luther;</hi> which is for one thouſand and foure hundred yeares or thereabouts, they are not able to aſſigne one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16729:18"/> Doctor, Preacher or Writer, that held or taught the doctrine Proteſtants doe now preach and teach.</p>
               <p>That our Catholike Romane Faith was planted by the Apoſtles and Diſciples of our Lord, and hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſucceſſiuely dilated ouer the world, according to theſe Prophecies, we haue proued in the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and third Chapters.</p>
               <p>Whereupon wee rightly inferre, that by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of <hi>Dauid</hi> and the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> our Sauiour was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith, and conclude this Chapter with the words of Saint AVGVSTINE, ſaying: <hi>We may ſee many accuſe themſelues of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. epiſt.</hi> 48:</note> 
                  <hi>blindneſſe, who could beleeue that Chriſt was exalted aboue the heauens, though they did not ſee it, and yet did deny that his glory was ouer all the earth, although they did ſee it: When the Prophet hath ſo clearely comprehended them both in one ſentence, ſaying: Be exalted aboue the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.</note> 
                  <hi>heauens, O God, and thy glory ouer all the earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the teſtimony of the Prophet</hi> Iſay, <hi>our Sauiour was Author of the Catholike Romane Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſpeaking more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly of the ſeed (Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which was to be planted by our Sauiour) then the reſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſaith: <hi>It is a ſmall thing, that thou</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhouldeſt bee my ſeruant, to raiſe the Tribes of</hi> Iacob, <hi>and to conuert the dregges of Iſrael. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I haue giuen thee to be a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayeſt be ſaluation, euen to the furtheſt part of the earth. Kings ſhall ſee, and Princes ſhall riſe and adore for</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:16729:19"/> 
                  <hi>our Lords ſake, becauſe he is faithfull, and for the holy one of Iſrael, who hath choſen thee.</hi> Againe, <hi>Behold I will</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 49. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>lift vp my hand to the Gentiles, and to the people I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt my ſigne. And they ſhall carry thy ſons in their armes, and thy daughters vpon their ſhoulders. And Kings ſhalbe thy nurſing fathers, and Queenes thy nurſes, with counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance caſt toward the ground, they ſhal adore thee, and they ſhal licke vp the dust of thy feete; and thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord.</hi> This Prophecie cannot be verified of Proteſtaniſme: Firſt, for that they were neuer yet any light to the Gentiles, and a ſaluation to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt part of the earth, that they might become Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; many Proteſtants denying Chriſtianity, become Turkes in <hi>Tranſiluania</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> and many Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh at <hi>Tripolis, Algiers</hi> and <hi>Tunis:</hi> And ſome learned Proteſtants, as <hi>Sebaſtian Ceſtalio, Bernard Ochine, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid George, Adam Neucers</hi> and others, who being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate againſt Catholike Religion, either turned Turkes or Iewes, ſeeing the Prophecies not fulfilled in Proteſtantiſme.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for that they are not able to produce any one Heathen or Pagan King or Queene, that hitherto hath embraced Proteſtaniſme. Your <hi>Maieſty</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian Kings and Queenes, your Predeceſſors, in the Kingdome of Great <hi>Brittanie,</hi> haue had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtendome, then that they haue receiued from Catholike Romane Prieſts.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It is not the cuſtome of Proteſtants to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore their God with ſuch reſpect or reuerence, as the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> heere ſpeakes of: euery Proteſtant is ſo well aſſured of his ſaluation, that hee hath no need to humble himſelfe befor his God; to aske forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes, or ſaluation of his ſoule. Not a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Boy or Girle, that doth not vſe more reſpect or reuerence to their maſters, when they ſpeake vnto
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16729:19"/> them, and all Proteſtants in their degrees and eſtates, to their temporall Lords and Princes; then they doe, when they pray, or ſpeake to their God. When they ſpeake to their earthly Lords or Kings; either they <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
                  </label> ſtand, or kneele handſomely, with their hats in their hands; but when they ſpeake to their God, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they either ſpeake ſitting, with their cappes on, as haile fellow well met with their God; or elſe with their noſes thruſt into their hats, for feare, as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that the euill ſmelles, which come from their God ſhould infect their braines. Their Temples and Synagogues are not ſo neate as their Bed-chambers, Galleries, or Chambers of Preſence or audience; and when they come into their Temples to treate with their God, or heare his Word or Law, vnleſſe it be for reſpect of ſome man there, euery one without reſpect to his God, ſitteth him downe, and putteth on his cap: In ſo much as the God of the Proteſtants, is the moſt vnciuill, euill-mannered God of all thoſe, who haue borne the name of Gods vpon earth, yea worſe then <hi>Pan,</hi> the god of Clownes, that can endure no ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies or good manners: whereby it is manifeſt, that this Prophecie is not verified vpon ſo vnciuill, and vnman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly a Religion as Proteſtantiſme is: but vpon our Catholike Romane Faith and Religion, which all the knowne Chriſtian Kings and Queenes, that euer haue been before <hi>Luther,</hi> profeſſed (reputed Heretikes by both parties onely excepted) as we haue ſet downe in the third Chapter.</p>
               <p>Againe, God Almightie by the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaith to the Gentiles, whom he calleth the barren women, for that before the Incarnation of our Sauiour, they were without fruit of eternall life. <hi>Prayſe O barren</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 54. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>woman which beareſt not, ſing prayſe and make ioyfull noyſe, which diddeſt not beare, becauſe many are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16729:20"/> 
                  <hi>of the deſolate</hi> (of the Gentiles which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comming of Chriſt deſolate of ſpiritual helpe) <hi>more then of her that hath a husband</hi> (the Synagogue of the Iewes) <hi>enlarge the place of thy tent, and ſtretch out the skins of thy Tabernacles, for thou ſhalt penetrate to the right hand, and to the left, and thy ſeed ſhall inherit the Gentiles.</hi> Againe: <hi>For a moment, a little while, haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 64. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>I forſaken thee, and in great mercies will I gather thee, in a moment of indignation haue I hid my face a little while from thee, and in mercies euerlaſting haue I had mercy on thee, ſaith thy Redeemer our Lord. As in the dayes of</hi> Noe, <hi>is this thing to me, to whom I ſware, that I would no more bring the waters of</hi> Noe <hi>vpon the earth. So haue I ſworne not to be angry with thee, and not to rebuke thee, for the mountaines ſhal be mooued, and the little hils ſhal tremble, but my mercy ſhal not depart from thee, and the couenant of my peace ſhal not be mooued, ſaith our Lord thy Miſerator.</hi> Againe, <hi>Euery veſſel that is made againſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 64. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>thee ſhal not proſper, and euery tongue reſiſting thee in iudgement, thou ſhalt iudge. This is the inheritance of the ſeruants of our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Prophecie of <hi>Eſay</hi> cannot bee verified vpon Proteſtantiſme, for that ſince our Sauiours time, there hath not been more Proteſtants then Iewes, neyther haue the children of the Proteſtants bin more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, then the children of the Iewes, who are a great people in number, and haue continued viſible in great numbers, diſperſed through many parts of the world, as Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe: as the Centurie Writers, in the fourteenth and fifteenth Chapter of euery Centurie, where they make mention from time to time of their abode, and at this day the Synagogue of the Iewes is more dilated, and greater then any one Sect of Proteſtants in the world.</p>
               <p>Secondly, neither can this be verified of Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16729:20"/> that after our Sauiours comming, <hi>They ſhould enlarge the place of their tents, penetrate to the right hand and the left, and that the ſeed of Proteſtants ſhould inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the Gentiles.</hi> Neither could this oath of God bee made to Proteſtants: <hi>I haue ſworne not to be angry with Proteſtants, and not to rebuke them; for the mountaines ſhal be moued, and the little hils ſhal tremble, but my mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſhal not depart from Proteſtants, and the couenant of my peace ſhal not be moued, ſaith our Lord thy Miſerator:</hi> vnleſſe they will make God Almighty forſworne, ſince they themſelues confeſſe that Proteſtantiſme vaniſhed away preſently after the Apoſtles times, and was ſo extinguiſhed, that for a thouſand and foure hundred yeares, they cannot name one Proteſtant man, that taught the doctrine they now teach. In ſuch ſort, as this malediction of the Prophecie is fulfilled in them, as vpon the enemies of our Sauiour; where it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Euery veſſel that is made againſt thee ſhal not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.</hi> And all the bleſſings of this Prophecie are veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vpon our Catholike Romane Faith, which was planted by the Apoſtles, and hath beene dilated ouer the world, and embraced of all Chriſtian people, who liued betweene the death of the Apoſtles and riſing of <hi>Luther,</hi> (reputed Heretikes to both parties only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) as wee haue prooued in the firſt, ſecond, and third Chapters.</p>
               <p>And by this oath of God heere ſet downe, it is as certaine that the Catholike Roman Church and Faith ſhall neuer bee ſuppreſſed; as it is certaine that the world ſhall not be drowned with water any more: the oath and promiſe of God Almightie being equally giuen for aſſurance of both, ſaying: <hi>As the day of</hi> Noe <hi>is this thing to me, to whom I anſwere, that I would no more bring in the waters of</hi> Noe <hi>vpon the earth: ſo haue I ſworne not to be angry with thee, or rebuke thee, for the</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16729:21"/> 
                  <hi>mountaines ſhal be moued, and the little hils ſhal tremble, but my mercy ſhall not depart from thee, and the couenant of my peace ſhal not be moued, ſaith our Lord thy Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator.</hi> And your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> may be pleaſed heere to obſerue, that thoſe Kings and people, who perſecute the Catholike Romane Faith, do but bring miſery and vnhappineſſe vpon themſelues, according to the word of God in this Prophecie, ſaying; <hi>Euery veſſel that is made againſt thee ſhal not proſper:</hi> and after all their rage and crueltie of hanging, drawing and quartering, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, and ſeuere Lawes made againſt Romane Catholikes, they muſt come to be judged by them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the words of God in this Prophecie, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>That euery tongue reſiſting thee in iudgement, thou ſhalt iudge, this is the inheritance of the ſeruants of our Lord</hi> (Ieſus Chriſt) <hi>and their iuſtice with me, ſaith our Lord;</hi> to bee Iudge of thoſe, who reſiſted them in judgement.</p>
               <p>Againe, God Almightie ſpeaking of the encreaſe of Chriſtian Religion, ſaith; <hi>Ariſe, be illuminated Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe thy light is come, &amp; the glory of our Lord is riſen vpon thee: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thee ſhal our Lord ariſe, and his glory ſhal be ſeene vpon thee. And the Gentiles ſhal walke in thy light, and Kings in the brightneſſe of thy riſing, lift vp thine eyes round about, and ſee al theſe gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they are come to thee: thy ſonnes ſhal come from a far, and daughters ſhal riſe from thy ſide. Then thou ſhalt ſee and abound, and thy heart ſhal maruaile and be enlarged, when the multitude of the ſea ſhal be conuerted vnto thee, the ſtrength of the Gentiles ſhal come to thee.</hi> Againe, <hi>For</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>the Ilands expect me, or the ſhips on the ſea in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that I may bring thy ſonnes from far.</hi> Againe, <hi>And</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>thy gates ſhalbe open continually, day &amp; night they ſhal not be ſhut, that the ſtrength of the Gentiles may be brought to thee, and their Kings may be brought. For the Nation</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16729:21"/> 
                  <hi>and the Kingdome that ſhal not ſerue thee, ſhal periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſe that there were Proteſtants in our Sauiour and the Apoſtles times, yet is it manifeſt that theſe Prophecies cannot be verified vpon them, <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould walke in the light of Proteſtantiſme, and Kings in the brightneſſe of their riſing, and the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the ſea be conuerted vnto them, and the ſtrength of the Gentiles, or that the Iſlands did expect Proteſtantiſme, and the ſhips of the ſea in the beginning, or that the gates of Proteſtants Temples, were open continually, day and night, that the ſtrength of the Gentiles might be brought to Proteſtaniſme, and their Kings.</hi> Since the Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe, that after the Apoſtles times Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſme vaniſhed away, and was no where ſo much as viſible, for a thouſand and foure hundred yeares. In ſuch ſort, as within all that ſpace they are not able to name any one man; much leſſe one Heathen or Pagan King, conuerted to the Religion they now profeſſe.</p>
               <p>So, ſuppoſe that in our Sauiours time there were Proteſtants, it is manifeſt that they were theſe enemies of Chriſtian Religion, vpon whom was verified this part of the Prophecie, ſaying; <hi>The Nation, and the Kingdome that ſhall not ſerue thee, ſhall periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, God Almightie ſpeaking of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans after our Sauiours comming, ſaith by the ſame Prophet: <hi>I will giue their workes in truth, and make a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay.</hi> 61.</note> 
                  <hi>perpetual couenant with them, and they ſhall know their ſeed in the Gentiles, and their bud in the middeſt of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, all that ſhall ſee them, ſhall know them, that theſe are the ſeed which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi> Againe, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>walles, Ieruſalem, I haue appointed watchmen, al the day, and al the night, for euer, they ſhal not hold their peace. And you that remember our Lord, hold not your peace, and giue not ſilence to him, vntil he ſtabliſh, and vntil he make Ieruſalem the praiſe in the earth. Our Lord hath ſworne</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:16729:22"/> 
                  <hi>by his right hand, and by the arme of his ſtrength: If I ſhall giue thy wheate any more, to be meate to thy enemies, and if the ſtrange children ſhall drinke thy wine, wherein thou haſt laboured. Becauſe they that ſhall gather it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhall eat it, and ſhall praiſe the Lord, and they that caried it together, ſhal drinke it in my holy courts.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that there were Proteſtants in our Sauiours &amp; the Apoſtles times, yet theſe Prophecies could not be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified vpon them, that God Almightie ſhould make a perpetuall couenant with Proteſtants, viſibly to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>their ſeed in the Gentiles, and their bud in the midſt of peoples.</hi> Neither can this oath be verified vpon Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: <hi>Our Lord hath ſworne by his right hand, and by the hand of his ſtrength, that he would giue the wheate of Proteſtants no more to be meat for their enemies, and that ſtrangers ſhould not drinke the wine, wherein Proteſtants haue laboured:</hi> who decayed preſently after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, as they confeſſe, and were ſo farre off from enioying theſe bleſſings heere promiſed, that all the maledictions prophecied to wicked and impious men, enemies to Gods truth, fell vpon them in ſuch ſort, that there is leſſe memorie of them, then of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorra,</hi> which was deſtroyed with fire from heauen, or of <hi>Coar, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiron,</hi> who were ſwallowed vp quicke into the earth; of whom there is ſome men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made in other mens writings. But of Proteſtants liuing after the Apoſtles times, who ſhould before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> hold, and teach the doctrine they now teach. No Author doth giue teſtimony of any ſuch men, or make ſo much mention of them, as of any of their names, or Countries where they dwelt, or where they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: wherefore it ſeemeth, that if euer they were in theſe times, they were enormous wicked vile peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, curſed of God aboue all the men that euer liued vpon the face of the earth; euen ſuch abominable
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16729:22"/> people, as all men were aſhamed to name, or make any mention of any one of them; <hi>people that deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell quicke,</hi> of whom they would keepe no memory. Now, that all theſe Prophecies are verified vpon our Catholike Romane Faith and Religion, we haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſhewed in the firſt, ſecond and third Chapters of this booke: whereupon we inferre, that by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> our Sauiour was Author of the <hi>Catholike Romane Faith,</hi> and planter of it vpon earth. And ſo conclude this Chapter with the words of Saint AVGVSTINE, ſaying: <hi>What can be exacted</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Vnit. Ecclae.</note> 
                  <hi>to be ſpoken more manifeſtly? Behold how many, and how cleare testimonies haue been brought out of one Prophet, and yet there is reſiſtance and contradiction made, not to any man, but to the Spirit of God, and to the moſt euident truth. And yet the glory of Chriſt is enuied by thoſe, who will boaſt of the name of Chriſtians, that thoſe things wbich haue been ſo long before foretolde of him, may not be beleeued to be fulfilled; whereas now they are not foretold, but ſhewed, ſeene and poſſeſſed.</hi> So Saint AVGVSTINE; and we with him.</p>
               <p>That theſe Prophecies of <hi>Iſay</hi> are ſpoken of the Church of Chriſt; Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe in the Collections of the Contents of the Chapters, ſet downe before euery Chapter, in their Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Bibles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:16729:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is proued by the teſtimony of the Prophet</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romie, <hi>that our Sauiour was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpeaking of the eſtate of the Church after our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours comming, ſaith: <hi>Behold the dayes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 31. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall come, ſaith our Lord, and I wil make a new couenant with the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And this ſhal be the couenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael: after theſe dayes ſaith the Lord, I will giue my Law in their bowels, and in their heart I will write it: I wil be their God, and they ſhal be my people. And a man ſhal no more teach his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and a man his brother, ſaying; Know our Lord, for all ſhal know me, from the leaſt of them, euen to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, ſaith our Lord, for I wil be merciful to their iniquitie, and their ſinne I wil remember no more. Thus ſaith our Lord that giueth the Sunne for the light of the day, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Moone, and of the Starres for the light of the night: that troubleth the ſea, and the waues thereof doe ſound, the Lord of hoſtes is his name: If theſe Lawes ſhal faile before me, ſaith our Lord,</hi> (that there be no more Sunne for the light of the day, and Moone and Stars for the light of the night, and ebbing and flowing of the Sea) <hi>then alſo the ſeed Iſrael ſhal faile, that it be not a Nation before me for euer.</hi> Wherupon our Sauiour ſaith; <hi>This Goſpel of the kingdome ſhal be preached in the whole</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>world, for a teſtimony to al Nations, and then ſhal come the conſummation of the world, and the Sun ſhal be darkened, and the Moone ſhal not giue her light, and the ſtars ſhal fall from heauen.</hi> Vntill then, if wee will beleeue the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16729:23"/> Word of God, the ſeed of our Sauiour, the Church of God ſhall in all ages and times ſo flouriſh vpon earth, as that the Chriſtians ſhall not neede, ſecretly one to teach another: <hi>But all ſhall know our Lord, from the leaſt of them to the greateſt, and be a viſible Nation for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So I appeale to your <hi>Maieſty</hi> well pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how ignorant hee ſhould bee in the Scriptures, that ſhould make himſelfe of the Congregation of Proteſtants, in hope to enter into this Teſtament with God, when they haue been ſo inuiſible for one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand and foure hundred yeares together, that they are not able to aſſigne one man, who for all that time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the Faith they now hold; much leſſe one Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So if Proteſtants would prooue by the Scriptures, that their Religion (which hath been ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares vnknowne) were the Faith planted by our Sauiour, they ſhould firſt proue, that for one thouſand and foure hundred yeares, there hath been no <hi>Sunne for the light of the day, or Moone for the light of the night,</hi> to make good the Word of God: otherwiſe they proue nothing, but that they are ignorant in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and in effect and deede, blaſpheme God and his holy Word, by affirming him in effect and deed, to be a violater of his promiſes written in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>That this promiſe of God heere ſpoken of, is to be performed in, and vpon Chriſtians: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the eight to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> where he repeateth the foreſaid words of <hi>Ieromie,</hi> as to be fulfilled in and vpon Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>That our Catholike Romane Faith hath ſucceſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continued according to this Prophecie, wee haue ſhewed in the firſt, ſecond and third Chapters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:16729:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is proued by the teſtimony of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> That our Sauiour was the Author of the Romane Catholike Faith.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prophet</hi> Ezechiel <hi>ſpeaking of the eſtate of the Church after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Sauiour, ſaith;</hi> I will ſaue <note place="margin">Ezech. 34.</note> my flocke, and it ſhalbe no more into ſpoile, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I will raiſe vp ouer them one Paſtor, who ſhall feed them; my ſeruant <hi>Dauid</hi> he ſhal feed them, and he ſhall be their Paſtor. And I the Lord wil be their God; and my ſeruant <hi>Dauid</hi> the Prince in the middeſt of them. I the Lord haue ſpoken, and I will make a couenant of peace with them, and will make the cruel beaſts to ceaſe out of the Land. And they that dwell in the deſart <hi>(the Hermits and religious men, who now, and in the Primatiue Church liued in the deſart, as witneſſeth Saint</hi> Auſtine, Epiſt. 121.) ſhall ſleep ſecure in the forroſt. And I will put them round about my hill <hi>(his Church)</hi> a bleſſing. And I will bring downe the ſhower in his time, there ſhall bee raynes of bleſſing <hi>(abundance of ſpirituall graces, and conſolations of the holy Ghoſt, according to the words of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſaying:</hi> He that beleeueth in me, out of his belly ſhal <note place="margin">Iohn 7. 38.</note> flow riuers of liuing water.) And the tree of the field <hi>(our Sauiour the Vine, or Oliue tree)</hi> ſhal giue his fruit, and <note place="margin">Iohn 15. Rom. 11.</note> the earth <hi>(humane nature, of which it is ſaid,</hi> thou art earth) ſhal giue his ſpring, and they ſhal be in their Land <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> without feare, and they ſhal know that I am the Lord, when I ſhal haue broken the chaines of their yoke, and ſhal haue deliuered them out of the hand of thoſe that rule ouer them. And they ſhal be no more for a ſpoile to the Gentiles,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16729:24"/> neither ſhal the beaſts of the earth deuoure them: but they ſhal dwel confidently without any terror, and I wil raiſe vp to them a bud of name, and they ſhal be no more diminiſhed for famine in the Land, neither ſhal they beare any more the reproach of the Gentiles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Prophecie to be ſpoken of our Sauiour vnder the name of</hi> Dauid; <hi>firſt, Proteſtants in their Bibles confeſſe it: ſecondly, it is manifeſt, for that</hi> Dauid <hi>the Prophet was dead many yeares before the time of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel. <hi>Yet this Prophecie cannot bee verified vpon Proteſtants, that Proteſtants ſhall liue in their Land without feare, deliuered out of the hand of thoſe who rule ouer them, and bee no more for a ſpoile to the Gentiles, nor be any more diminiſhed, nor beare any more the reproch of the Gentiles, ſince they haue bin ſo ſpoiled and oppreſſed for one thouſand and foure hundred yeares together, that during all that time, they are not able to aſſigne one knowne man, who profeſſed the Religion they now profeſſe. This Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie to be verified vpon Romane Catholikes, wee haue ſhewed in the firſt, ſecond and third Chapters.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is proued by the teſtimony of the Prophets,</hi> Daniel, Ioel, Micheas, Abacuc, <hi>and</hi> Zacharias, <hi>That our Sauiour was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND in like manner all the reſt of the Prophets, as often as they haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake of the eſtate of the Church, after the comming of our Sauiour, ſay; that it ſhal be vniuerſally dilated ouer the world for euer, as <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſaying: <hi>In the dayes of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 44.</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16729:25"/> 
                  <hi>thoſe Kingdomes, the God of heauen wil raiſe vp a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that ſhal not be deſtroyed for euer, and this Kingdom ſhal not be deliuered to another people: and it ſhal breake in peeces, &amp; ſhal conſume al thoſe Kingdoms, &amp; it ſelf ſhal ſtand for euer.</hi> Which Prophecie we finde verified by experience vpon the Catholike Roman Church, which as Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe, was ſo potent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the Apoſtles times, that it deſtroyed and conſumed the Church of Proteſtants, and for theſe one thouſand and two hundred yeares hath raigned vniuerſally, without any debatable contradiction, as is ſet downe in the third Chapter. Againe, we ſee by experience, that all other Kingdomes and Monarchies of Chriſtians haue been interrupted and changed; as the <hi>Empire</hi> firſt from the Weſt vnto the Eaſt, and after into <hi>Germany: Spaine</hi> was firſt poſſeſſed by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> after by the <hi>Goathes,</hi> and laſtly, for many yeares by the <hi>Moores: France</hi> was long time tributarie to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and about the yeare of our Lord 451. the <hi>Franck Germanes,</hi> who dwelled beyond the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to conquer them, and in proceſſe of time obtained their Kingdome, and changed their name from <hi>Gaules</hi> to <hi>French;</hi> and about the yeare 461. elected <hi>Mirouee</hi> for King: after <hi>France</hi> was poſſeſſed by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt was crowned King of <hi>France,</hi> about the yeare 1422. from which time the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> haue alwayes challenged to be Kings of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>England</hi> was vnder the <hi>Romanes</hi> vntill the time of <hi>Honorius,</hi> and ſhortly after it was conquered by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and then by the <hi>Danes,</hi> and laſt by <hi>Norman French:</hi> In ſo much as that it is manifeſt to experience, that the Catholike Romane Church is the Kingdome rayſed vp by God, which ſhall not bee deſtroyed for euer.</p>
               <p>Whereupon the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> ſaith: <hi>Yee children of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. 23.</note>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:16729:25"/> 
                  <hi>Syon</hi> (the Church of God) <hi>reioyce and be ioyfull in the Lord your God, becauſe he hath giuen you a Doctor of iuſtice, and hee will make the earely and the late ſhowre to deſcend to you, as in the beginning. And the floores ſhal be filled with wheate, and the preſſes ſhall ouerflow with wine and oyle. And I wil render you the yeares which the Locuſt, the Bruke, and the blaſt, and the Eruke hath eaten: my great ſtrength which I haue ſent vpon you. And eating, you ſhal eate, and ſhal be filled, and you ſhal praiſe the name of the Lord your God, that hath done maruailes with you, and my people ſhal not be confounded for euer. And you ſhal know that I am in the middeſt of Iſrael, and I the Lord your God, and there is none beſides, and my people ſhal not be confounded for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Prophet <hi>Micheas</hi> ſaith: <hi>And thou Bethelem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Ephrata art a little one in the thouſands of Iuda, out of thee ſhall come forth vnto me, he that ſhal be the Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in Iſrael: and his comming forth from the beginning, from the dayes of eternity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the remnant of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſhal be conuerted to the children of Iſrael: And he ſhal ſtand and feed in the ſtrength of our Lord, in the height of the name of our Lord his God; and they ſhal be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe now ſhal he be magnified, euen to the ends of the earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And the remnant of</hi> Iacob <hi>ſhal be in the Gentiles, in the middeſt of many peoples, as a Lyon amongst the beaſts of the forreſt, and as a Lyons whelpe amongst the flocke of cattell, who when he hath paſſed, and trodden downe and taken, there is none to deliuer. Thy hand ſhall be exalted ouer thine enemies, and thine enemies ſhall periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Prophet <hi>Abacuc</hi> ſaith: <hi>God wil come from</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abac.</hi> 4. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>the South, and the holy one from the ſhady mountaine, his glory ſhal couer the heauens, and the earth is full of his praiſe.</hi> That is, ſaith S. AVGVSTINE, the Goſpell ſhall begin from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Mount Oliuet,</hi> and ſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16729:26"/> be dilated ouer the world: <hi>For Ieruſalem</hi> (ſaith Saint AVGVSTINE) <hi>is placed Southward, as is read in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p.</hi> 166.</note> 
                  <hi>booke of</hi> Ieſus Naue, <hi>from whence the name of Chriſt hath been ſpread, and there is a ſhadie mountaine, Mount Oliuet; from whence he aſcended into heauen, that his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue might couer the heauens, and the Church might be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with his praiſe, throughout the whole earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Prophet <hi>Zacharias</hi> ſaith: <hi>Behold thy King will come to thee, the luſt, and Sauiour: himſelfe, poore and riding vpon an Aſſe, and vpon a Colt, the Fole of an Aſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He ſhal ſpeake peace to the Gentiles, and his power from ſea, euen to ſea, and from the riuers</hi> (of <hi>Iordan,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 13.</note> where he was baptiſed) <hi>euen vnto the end of the earth;</hi> not for a day, or a month, or a yeare: <hi>But as he ſpake to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>our Fathers, to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his ſeed for euer.</hi> Theſe Prophecies to be verified on our Catholike Roman Faith, we haue ſhewed at large in the firſt, ſecond, and third Chapter, and are ſo far from being verified vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Proteſtantiſme, that for a thouſand and foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares together Proteſtants are not able to name one man, who held and taught the doctrine, they now hold and teach.</p>
               <p>So dread <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> if the teſtimonies of <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> may find grace and credit with your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> they affirme that our Sauiour was Author of the Catholike Romane Faith, as we haue abundantly ſhewed. Yet the teſtimonies of <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> were of ſuch force with our Sauiour, as he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaying; <hi>If they heare not</hi> Moyſes <hi>and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>the Prophets, neither wil they be perſwaded though one riſe from the dead.</hi> Againe, hee ſaith to the incredulous Iewes; <hi>Had you beleeued</hi> Moyſes, <hi>you would peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 46.</note> 
                  <hi>haue beleeued me, for he wrote of me. And if you beleeue not his writings,</hi> (which are confirmed by ſo many oathes, and promiſes, and found true by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16729:26"/> experience) <hi>how wil you beleeue my words?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I conclude the Prophecies of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the words of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ſaying: <hi>The</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Prophets haue ſpoken more obſcurely of Chriſt, then of the Church, I thinke, becauſe they did ſee in ſpirit, that men would rebell againſt the Church, and would not haue ſo great ſtrife concerning Chriſt, but would raiſe vp great contentions concerning the Church: therefore, that about which men were to make great ſtrife, was more plainly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, and more manifeſtly prophecied; that it might ſerue for their condemnation, who did ſee it, and fled out.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is proued by the teſtimony of Angels, that our Sauiour was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING (moſt dread <hi>Soueraigne)</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the counſel of our Sauiour, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 39.</note> ſought the old Teſtament, to ſee what it ſaith of the Faith, Seed, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and hauing found that by it, our Lord was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith, Seed or Religion: we will now deſcend downe vnto the New, to ſee what it ſaith in generall, of the Faith, Seed, Word, or Goſpel, which our Sauiour planted vpon earth: that wee may alſo ſee, whether according to the teſtimonie of the new Teſtament, our Lord was Author of our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Faith and Religion.</p>
               <p>And firſt the Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> foretelling the eſtate of the Church to come, ſaith to our bleſſed Lady, <hi>Thou</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhalt conceiue in thy wombe, and ſhalt beare a Sonne, and thou ſhalt call his name</hi> IESVS, <hi>he ſhal be great, and he</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16729:27"/> 
                  <hi>ſhal be called the Son of the moſt High, and our Lord God ſhal giue him the ſeat of</hi> Dauid <hi>his Father, and he ſhal reigne in the houſe of</hi> Iacob <hi>for euer, and of his Kingdome there ſhal be no end.</hi> And in like manner, an Angell of our Lord ſaid vnto the Shepheards: <hi>Behold, I euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>to you great ioy that ſhal be to al people;</hi> not to one people of <hi>Brittans,</hi> or <hi>Germans,</hi> but <hi>to al people: becauſe this day is borne to you a Sauiour, which is Chriſt our Lord. And ſuddenly there was with the Angel a multitude of the heauenly armie</hi> (a multitude of Angels) <hi>prayſing God, and ſaying: Glory in the higheſt to God, and in earth Peace to men of good wil.</hi> As it was foretold by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſay,</hi> ſaying: <hi>A little childe is borne to vs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>His Empire ſhalbe multiplied, and there ſhalbe no end of peace: he ſhal ſit vpon the throne of</hi> Dauid, <hi>and vpon his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: that he may confirme it, in iudgement and iuſtice, from this time, and for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Kingdome heere ſpoken of, is the Church profeſſing the Faith, or Goſpell planted by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, our Lord himſelfe doth witneſſe, ſaying: <hi>In the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>end of the world, the Sonne of Man ſhall ſend his Angels, and they ſhal gather out of his Kingdome all ſcandals, and them that worke iniquity.</hi> Againe, <hi>And this Goſpell of the Kingdom ſhal be preached in the whole world.</hi> Againe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>And Ieſus went about teaching, and preaching the Goſpel</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if the Angels of God, and multitude of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Armie, may finde grace and credite with your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> to be beleeued by their teſtimonies, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that our Sauiour came to plant the Catholike Romane Church and Faith: which, as we haue proued in our firſt Chapter, was taught by our Sauiour, and planted by the Apoſtles amongſt the Romans, &amp; hath continued, and ſhall continue amongſt them vntill the day of Iudgement: and as is confeſſed by Proteſtants,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16729:27"/> hath reigned vniuerſally: without any debatable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, 1200. yeares, as is ſet downe in the third Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is proued by the teſtimony of our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Lord &amp; Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing that many Heretikes would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe; and ſay, that his Seede, Faith, Word, Church, or Goſpell had failed and decayed, and that they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly ſent from God, to plant a new Faith, or reforme or reſtore the Goſpell, &amp;c. To preuent their hereticall falſehood, hee warneth all his faithfull that they ſhould not beleeue them, ſaying: <hi>Doe not thinke that I came to breake the Law</hi> (the olde <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 18.</note> Teſtament) <hi>or the Prophets, I am not come to breake, but to fulfill; for aſſuredly I ſay to you, Till heauen and earth paſſe, one iot, or one tittle ſhall not paſſe of the Law</hi> (the olde Teſtament) <hi>till all be fulfilled;</hi> and the Church of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 2.</note> God, begunne in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Iuda,</hi> be dilated to the Weſt, and to the Eaſt, and to the North, and to the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.</note> South, <hi>as God ſpake to Abraham and his ſeed for euer.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So ſuppoſed that our Sauiours words are true, and that hee was the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and came to fulfill and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the things promiſed by the Prophets, and not to breake or violate their promiſes; the Sunne was neuer more manifeſt in the moneth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> then it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that he fulfilled the Prophecies, by planting the Catholike Romane Faith, and not by planting Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſme,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16729:28"/> ſince Romane Catholikes haue been viſibly multiplied ouer the world, for many hundred yeares; ſome Proteſtants ſay for nine hundred years, ſome ſay for a thouſand, other Proteſtants ſay for twelue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and others ſay for more, as is ſet downe in the third Chapter: whereas the Prophecies haue beene ſo farre off from being fulfilled in Proteſtantiſme, that preſently after the death of the Apoſtles it vaniſhed away, and hath been no where viſibly knowne, for one thouſand foure hundred yeares. So we may ſpeak to Proteſtants (who imagine that their Religion is true, or was the Faith planted by our Sauiour) and ſay to them in the words of our Sauiour: <hi>Doe not thinke that our Sauiour came to break the Law or the Prophets,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>he came not to breake, but to fulfill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, our Sauiour foretelling the eſtate of his Church to come, ſaith: <hi>All things muſt needs be fulfilled which are writted in the Law of</hi> Moyſes, <hi>and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 44. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Pſalmes of me.</hi> And the Law of <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſaith: <hi>I wil multiply thy ſeed as the Starres of heauen,</hi> &amp;c. The Prophets ſay; <hi>Behold thy King will come to thee, the Iuſt one, and Sauiour, himſelfe poore and riding vpon an</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 9. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He ſhal ſpeake Peace to the Gentiles, and his power from ſea, euen to ſea, and from the riuers, euen to the end of the earth.</hi> Againe, <hi>And I wil ſend of them that ſhal be ſaued to the Gentiles into the ſea, into Aſricke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.</note> 
                  <hi>and Lidia, into Italy and Greece, to the Ilands farre off, to them that haue not heard of me, and haue not ſeene my glory. And they ſhal ſhew forth my glory to the Gentiles, and they ſhal bring of your brethren of al Nations, a gift to our Lord, vpon horſes, and in chariots, and in horſelit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and on Mules, and in coatches, to my holy mountaine Ieruſalem. Becauſe, as new heauens, and a new earth, which I make to ſtand before me, ſaith our Lord, ſo ſhal your ſeed ſtand, and your name.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmes</hi> ſay. <hi>Al the</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16729:28"/> 
                  <hi>ends of the earth ſhal remember and be conuerted to our</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord: and all the families of the Gentiles ſhal adore in his ſight.</hi> Againe, <hi>Thou art my ſonne, this day haue I begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>thee, aske of me, and I will giue thee the Gentiles for thine inheritance, and thy poſſeſſion the ends of the earth.</hi> Againe, <hi>I wil put his ſeed for euer and euer, and his throne</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.</note> 
                  <hi>as the dayes of heauen. I haue ſworne in my holy, if I lye to</hi> Dauid <hi>his ſeed ſhal continue for euer.</hi> All which, and many more the like promiſes and Prophecies, of the encreaſe, continuance, and dilatation of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the ſeed of our Sauiour, the ſeed of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> ouer the world, <hi>muſt</hi> (as our Sauiour <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 44.</note> ſaith) <hi>needs be fulfilled,</hi> and yet we ſee by experience, that they are fulfilled in no other people kindred, or Nation, but Romane Catholikes, whom Proteſtants confeſſe to haue reigned vniuerſally ouer the world, for twelue hundred yeares, as is ſet downe in the third Chapter. And ſo I conclude out of our Sauiours words, that the Catholike Romane Faith, muſt needs be the Faith and Religion which our Sauiour planted, and that Romane Catholikes are true Chriſtians, ſince neither the promiſes in the bookes of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> nor in the Prophets, nor in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> are, or can bee veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or fulfilled in, or vpon any other.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, our Sauiour ſpeaking of the eſtate of his Church, ſaith: <hi>The Kingdome of heauen is reſembled vnto a man that ſowed good ſeed in his field, but when men</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>were aſleepe, his enemies came and ouer-ſowed Cockle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Wheate, and went his way, and when the blade was ſhut vp, and had brought forth fruit, then appeared al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Cockle. And the ſeruants of the Good-man of the houſe, comming, ſaid to him: Sir, diddeſt thou not ſowe good ſeed in thy field? Whence then hath it Cockle? and he ſaid to them; the enemie man hath done this. And the ſeruants ſaid to him, Wilt thou we goe, and gather it vp?</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:16729:29"/> 
                  <hi>And he ſaid noe: leſt perhaps gathering vp the Cockle, you may roote vp the Wheate alſo, together with it, ſuffer both to grow vntill the harueſt: and in the time of haruest I wil ſay to the Reapers, Gather vp firſt the Cockle, and bind it into bundles to burne; but the wheate gather yee into my Barne.</hi> And expounding this Parable of the Cockle of the field, he ſaid to his Diſciples; <hi>He that ſowed the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>good ſeed is the Son of Man, and the field is the world, and the good ſeed, thoſe are the children of the Kingdome, and the Cockle, thoſe are the children of the wicked one, and the enemy that ſowed them is the Diuell: but the Harueſt is the end of the world, and the Reapers are the Angels.</hi> So our Sauiour in deſcribing his Church, by which deſcription it is manifeſt, that our Sauiour ſowed the Catholike Romane Faith, and that Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes are the children of the Kingdome of God, and all other Sects, of what kinde or ſort ſoeuer, are Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle ſowed by the Diuell, after death, or at the end of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 38.</note> the world, to be gathered vp and caſt into a <hi>Furnace of fire.</hi> Since there neither is at this inſtant, nor yet hath been heretofore any Nation, People, Faith, Religion, or Sect, which challenged the name of Chriſtians, that hath been ſucceſſiuely dilated ouer the world, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Sauiours deſcription, but the Catholike Romane Faith, which as <hi>Perkins,</hi> a Proteſtant, ſaith: <note place="margin">Vpon the Creed. <hi>fol.</hi> 307.</note> 
                  <hi>During the ſpace of nine hundred yeares, ſpread it ſelfe ouer the whole earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, our Sauiour ſpeaking of his Church, ſaith: <hi>The Kingdome of heauen is like vnto a muſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>which a man tooke and ſowed in his field; which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the leaſt ſurely of all ſeeds, but when it is growne, it is greater then all hearbes, and is made a tree, ſo that the fowles of the ayre come to dwell in the branches thereof.</hi> Againe, <hi>The Kingdome of heauen is like to Leauen, which</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>a woman tooke and hid in three meaſures of meale, vntill</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:16729:29"/> 
                  <hi>the whole was leauened.</hi> Againe, <hi>The Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>is like to a net, caſt into the ſea, and gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all kinde of fiſhes.</hi> Which words of our Sauiour cannot bee verified vpon Proteſtantiſme, ſuppoſing that it was in the Apoſtles times, as they affirme, ſince it did not encreaſe or grow greater then al other ſects, nor leauened the whole world, nor gathered together all kinde of people. But ſo vaniſhed away after the Apoſtles departure, that for fourteene hundred yeares together they are not able to aſſigne one man, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Religion they doe now.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Our Sauiour ſetting downe the ſtate of his Church to come, ſaith: <hi>I choſe you, and haue appointed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>you, that you go and bring fruit, and your fruit abide.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>This Goſpell of the Kingdome ſhal be preached in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>the whole world, for a teſtimony to all Nations, and then ſhal come the conſummation.</hi> Againe. <hi>Holy Father, I pray</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>not that thou take them away out of this world, but that thou preſerue them from euill,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And not for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles only do I pray, but for them alſo that by their words, ſhal beleeue in me.</hi> Againe, <hi>Teach yee all Nations, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>behold I am with you all daies, euen to the end of the world.</hi> Which words of our Sauiour cannot be verified vpon Proteſtants, that our Sauiour hath appointed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to goe and preach in the world, and bring fruit, and their fruit abide; or that Proteſtantiſme ſhould be preached to all Nations; or that our Sauiour prayed that Proteſtants ſhould not be taken away out of the world, but be preſerued from euill; or that our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our would be with Proteſtants, ayding and aſſiſting them in the conuerſion of Nations, <hi>euen to the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>of the world:</hi> ſince wee ſee it falſe by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, Our Sauiour ſpeaking of the eſtate of his Church, ſaith to the chiefe Prieſts, and Ancients of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16729:30"/> people: <hi>Haue you neuer read in the Scriptures; The ſtone</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>which the builders reiected, the ſame is made the head of the corner. By our Lord was it done, and it is marueilous in our eyes. Therefore I ſay to you, that the Kingdome of God ſhall be taken away from you, and giuen to a Nation yeelding the fruit thereof. And he that falleth vpon that ſtone ſhal be broken, and on whom it falleth, it ſhal al to bruiſe him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words of our Sauiour cannot be verified vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Proteſtants, that our Sauiour ſhould become head, to vnite Iewes and Proteſtants together in one family of Chriſtians: or ſhould take away his Church, and Kingdome vpon earth, from the Iewes, to giue it to Proteſtants, or that the Church of Proteſtants ſhould yeeld more fruit then the Church of the Iewes, or he that ſhould fall vpon the Church of Proteſtants ſhould be broken: ſince as <hi>Sebaſtianus Francus,</hi> a Proteſtant, <note place="margin">In epiſt. de Abro. ſtat. Eccl.</note> affirmeth; That for certaine, <hi>through the worke of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, the external Church</hi> (of Proteſtants) <hi>together with the Faith &amp; Sacraments, vaniſhed away preſently after the Apoſtles departure, and that for theſe fourteene hundred yeares, the Church</hi> (of Proteſtants) <hi>hath bin no where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and viſible.</hi> Which being ſo, dread <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> I appeale to your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> wel pleaſed to conſider, how ignorant hee ſhould be in the Scriptures, that ſhould make himſelfe a Proteſtant, out of hope to become one of the Kingdome of God, heere ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>That all theſe promiſes and Prophecies of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour are verified vpon Papiſts; Proteſtants themſelues giue ſufficient teſtimonie, who affirme that Papiſtrie began in the time of the Apoſtles, and hath raigned vniuerſally for twelue hundred yeares, as is ſet downe in the third Chapter.</p>
               <p>So if the words and teſtimonies of our Sauiour himſelfe, may finde ſo much grace and fauour with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16729:30"/> your <hi>Maieſty</hi> as to be credited, it is manifeſt that by this teſtimony and deſcription of his Church, that he was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is proued by the teſtimony of the Apoſtles, that our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt was the Author of the Catholike Romane Faith.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of the eſtate of the Church planted by our Sauiour, ſaith: MOYSES <hi>indeed ſaid, that a Prophet ſhal the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord your God raiſe vp to you, of your brethren, as my ſelfe, him ſhal you heare, according to al things whatſoeuer he ſhal ſpeake to you. And it ſhal be, euery ſoule that ſhal not heare that Prophet, ſhal be deſtroyed out of the people. And al the Prophets from</hi> Samuel <hi>and afterward, that haue ſpoken, could of theſe dayes: you are the children of the Prophets, and of the Teſtament which God made to our Fathers, ſaying to</hi> Abraham: <hi>and in thy ſeed ſhal all the Families of the earth be bleſſed. To you firſt God raiſing vp his Sonne, hath ſent him, bleſſing you.</hi> That this Seed heere ſpoken of, is the Church of Chriſtians, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> do witneſſe, ſaying: <hi>The good ſeed, thoſe are the children of the Kingdome.</hi> Againe: <hi>If you</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 38. <hi>Galath.</hi> 3. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>be Chriſts, then are you the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>heires ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That this bleſſing can no way bee verified vpon Proteſtantiſme, is manifeſt, for that it vaniſhed away preſently after the time of the Apoſtles, and for faure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene hundred yeares together, there is not to be found one man that profeſſed it, much leſſe one Family, or all the Families of the earth. That this bleſſing in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16729:31"/> hath been verified vpon Roman Catholikes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants themſelues confeſſe; ſome Proteſtants affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that Papiſtry hath been ſpread ouer the world for nine hundred yeares, ſome for a thouſand, ſome for twelue hundred, and ſome for more, as it is ſet downe in the third Chapter.</p>
               <p>So if the teſtimony of Saint <hi>Peter, Moyſes,</hi> and all the Prophets, from <hi>Samuel</hi> and afterward, may finde ſo much grace and fauour with your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> as to be credited; they all affirme that our Sauiour was to bee the Author of our Catholike Romane Faith. And ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that there were Proteſtants in our Sauiours and the Apoſtles times, who after their departure vaniſhed away (as Proteſtants affirme) it is manifeſt by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Moſes</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> that they were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Chriſtian Religion, and ſo were deſtroyed from among the people, according to the words of <hi>Moyſes</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Euery ſoule that ſhal</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>not heare that Prophet, ſhal be deſtroyed out of the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Saint <hi>Poter</hi> ſpeaking of the eſtate of the Church, ſaith: <hi>Behold I put in Syon a principall corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>elect, preciaus. And he that ſhal beleeue in him, ſhal not be confounded. To you therefore that beleeue, honor; but to them that beleeue not, the ſtone which the builders reiected, the ſame is made into the head of the corner, and a ſtone of offence, and a Rocke of ſcandall to them that ſtumble at the Word,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But you</hi> (who beleeue) <hi>are an elect generation, a Kingly Prieſthood, a holy Nation, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of purchaſe, that you may declare his vertues, which from darkneſſe hath called you into his marueilous light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſed that there were Proteſtants in our Sauiours time, yet theſe words of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> cannot be verified vpon them, that they ſhould not bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founted, but honored, and made an elect generation, a Kingly Prieſthood, or holy Nation, a people of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16729:31"/> to declare our Sauiours vertues in fulfilling the promiſes, by conuerting the Gentiles to the Chriſtian Faith: Since they vaniſhed away preſently after the departure of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribing the eſtate of the Church to come, ſaith: <hi>Chriſt aſcending on high, he led captiuity captiue, he gaue gifts to men. And he gaue ſome</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and other ſome Euangeliſts, and other ſome Paſtors, and Doctors, to the conſummation of the Saints, vnto the worke of the Miniſtery, vnto the edifying of the body of Chriſt, vntill we meet all into the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Faith, and knowledge of the Sonne of God, that now we be not children, wauering, and carried about with euery winde of doctrine, in the wickedneſſe of men, in craftineſſe to the circumuention of error:</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribing the eſtate of the Church to come. If this be ſpoken of the Church of Proteſtants, where were their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> for fourteene hundred years together? Since for all that time, they are not able to aſſigne one man, who held the doctrine they now hold, much leſſe one <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Euangeliſt, Paſtor, or Doctor:</hi> and yet Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that they ſhould teach and preach truth, euen vnto the <hi>Conſummation of the Saints,</hi> that the Church might not be wauering, and carried about with euery winde of doctrine, in the wickedneſſe of men; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſee, that if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> were a true <hi>Apoſtle</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> the Church of Proteſtants is a falſe Church: That this Prophecie of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is verified vpon Roman Catholikes is manifeſt, for that Romane Catholikes haue had Doctors, Preachers, and Teachers, in all ages, as we haue proued in the firſt, ſecond, and third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>Againe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the eſtate of the Church to come, ſaith: <hi>God according to his promiſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:16729:32"/> 
                  <hi>hath brought forth to Iſrael a Sauiour.</hi> Againe, <hi>We preach</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto you that promiſe which was made to our Fathers,</hi> which was, <hi>I will multiply thy ſeed as the Starres of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.</note> &amp;c. <hi>As God ſpake to our Fathers, to</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>his ſeed for euer:</hi> which words and preaching of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould be falſe, if Proteſtantiſme were the Faith and Religion planted by our Sauiour, and Preached by Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> ſince it hath been ſo farre off from ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the promiſe, that it vaniſhed away preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apoſtles times.</p>
               <p>Againe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the eſtate of the Church, ſaith: <hi>By the offence of the Iewes, ſaluation is to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the Gentiles, that they may emulate them: And if the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Iewes be the riches of the world, and the dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of the Iewes the riches of the Gentiles? how much more the fulneſſe of them?</hi> Againe, <hi>If the loſſe of the Iewes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>be the reconciliation of the world, what ſhal the receiuing be?</hi> Againe, <hi>Blindneſſe in part hath chanced in Iſrael, vntill the fulneſſe of the Gentiles might enter, and ſo all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael might be ſaued:</hi> Which cannot bee verified vpon Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſme, ſuppoſed it were in the Apoſtles times, ſince Proteſtants haue neither been ſo eminent, as that the Iewes ſhould emulate them, nor the riches of the Gentiles, neither hath the world been reconciled to Proteſtantiſme, neither hath the fulneſſe of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles entred into Proteſtantiſme, which for fourteene hundred yeares together was not knowne vnto the men of the earth: That all theſe words of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> are verified vpon Romane Catholikes, Proteſtants themſelues giue ample teſtimony, as is ſet down here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore.</p>
               <p>By theſe and many more Prophecies of the eſtate of the Church to come, ſet downe by the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts, it is manifeſt that our Sauiour was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Catholike Romane Faith.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:16729:32"/>
               <p> So dread <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> if the Generall conſent of both Teſtaments, the teſtimonie of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> of <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> of <hi>Prophets,</hi> of <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> of <hi>Euangelists,</hi> and of all knowne <hi>Chriſten</hi> men that euer were before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> may find grace and credite with your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> to be beleeued; they all (reputed Heretikes by both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties onely excepted) affirme that the Sonne of <hi>God</hi> was Author of that Catholike Romane Faith, which is now perſecuted within your Dominions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Anſweres to Obiections.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="object">
                  <head>OBIECT. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Proteſtants doe not affirme, that their Congregation hath been inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for theſe fourteene hundred years, which were betweene the death of the Apoſtles, and the riſing of <hi>Luther:</hi> but ſome ſay that they were viſibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in the world, adminiſtrating the Sacraments, and preaching the pure Word.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Theſe Proteſtants did not liue in any of thoſe ages, to affirme that which they did ſee, Reuelations, Miracles, &amp; Traditions they deny, Writings, Records, Antiquities, Councels, Hiſtories, or any ancient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſuch a viſible company ſo adminiſtrating of Sacraments, they haue none; yet there is no other meanes of knowing things paſt, but by a vaine imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of an idle braine, proper to lunatike men in Bedlam and Bridewell, who talke of ſtrange phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and chimeraes, we looke for a people that <hi>ſhould</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:16729:33"/> 
                     <hi>be made Princes ouer all the earth: To whom Kings were</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.</note> 
                     <hi>nurſing fathers, and Queenes nurſes. That did ouerflow</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.</note> 
                     <hi>the glory of the Gentiles. That did poſſeſſe the gates of their</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.</note> 
                     <hi>enemies, in whoſe ſeed all the Nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed:</hi> And they tell vs of a people, that ſuppoſed they were, yet they were the moſt baſe, vile, contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, and wretched people, that euer liued vpon the earth: ſuch lyars and diſſemblers, as that it could not be knowne what Religion they profeſſed: So impious, that it is neuer heard of, that euer they vſed any Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Sermons, or Prayers: So barbarous, that it is not found vpon any Record, that euer they were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, but if they were, it ſeemeth that they accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied together like horſes and dogges: ſo ignorant, that there is not found one man amongſt them, that euer writ any thing: ſo vile that they neuer did any thing worthy of memory: So lawleſſe, that there is not found any Order, Statute, or Decree they had; ſuch Rogues and Vacabonds, that none vntill this day can finde out where any of them dwelt: Such enemies of Chriſt, and Chriſtianity, that not any teſtimonie can be found of their being Baptized, or Chriſtened: So if they were, it ſeemeth that they were rather the ſeed of the Diuell, then of <hi>Abraham</hi> or <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> or of any Chriſtian man.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 2. <hi>Waldo,</hi> who liued in the yeare of our Lord God 1220. and <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> who liued in the yeare of our Lord 1370. and <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> who liued in the yeare 1400. were Proteſtants, and held and taught the ſame doctrine Proteſtants doe now.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Waldo</hi> did ſo extoll merit for good works, that he did forſake all things to become poore, and follow Chriſt and euangelicall perfection, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth Doctor <hi>Humfrey,</hi> a Proteſtant, in his <hi>Ieſuitiſme, part.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 270. Secondly, hee denied the Sabbath, in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16729:33"/> regard whereof, the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> were called <hi>Inſabbatiſts,</hi> that is to ſay, people who had no Sabbath: as affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Fox, Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments fol.</hi> 41. Thirdly, hee taught that Lay-men and women might conſecrate the Sacrament, and preach. Fourthly, that there ſhould be no diuiſion of Pariſhes, Fiftly, that men ought not to ſweare in any caſe. Sixtly, That neither Prieſt, nor Ciuill Magiſtrate, being guiltie of mortall ſinne, did enjoy their dignities; or were to be obeyed: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the like, as witneſſeth ILLIRICVS <hi>in catel. teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um veritatis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wickliffe</hi> taught, that if a Biſhop or Prieſt were in deadly ſinne, his ordaining of Prieſts, Conſecrating, and Baptiſme, was not <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alide,</hi> and that Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters ſhould not haue any Temporall poſſeſſions, <hi>Fox</hi> Acts fol. 96. Moreouer, hee condemned lawfull oathes, as affirmeth <hi>Oſiander</hi> in his <hi>Epito. hist. Eccleſ. fol.</hi> 459. Yet maintained he the worſhipping of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, interceſſion to our bleſſed Lady, the Maſſe, and ſeuen Sacraments, as is manifeſt in his bookes.</p>
                  <p>And for <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> except the doctrine of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in both kinds, which he would haue giuen to Lay-men: and the doctrine of <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> in defending, that if a Prince, Prieſt, or Biſhop, committed mortall ſinne, they did loſe their dignities, and were not to be obeyed, for the moſt part he retained the Articles of our Catholike Faith, as the Seuen <hi>Sacraments,</hi> the Popes <hi>Primacie,</hi> the <hi>Maſſe;</hi> in ſo much as <hi>Luther in Colloquijs Germanicis, ca. de Antechristo,</hi> ſaith of him: <hi>The Papists burned</hi> Iohn Huſſe, <hi>when as yet he depapted not a fingers breadth from the Papacie, for he taught the ſame which Papiſts doe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 3. The Church of the Proteſtants was in that of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſo if Proteſtants were not, neither ſhould <hi>Papiſts</hi> be.</head>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:16729:34"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is to confeſſe that the Papiſts Church is the true Church, and that Proteſtants are Schiſmatikes or Heretikes, according to the Scriptures, ſaying: <hi>They went out from vs, but they were not of vs, for if they had</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>been of vs, they would ſurely haue remained with vs.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Out of your ſelues ſhall ariſe men ſpeaking peruerſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 4. The Church is compared to the Moone, ſo it may encreaſe, and diminiſh, and yet bee a true Church.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Church is compared to the Moone, not for that it waneth, &amp; increaſeth euery month, as the Moon in our <hi>Horiſon</hi> doth, but for becauſe what it loſeth in one Countrey, it gaineth in another, as what light the Moone wanteth on the one ſide, it hath on the other; and ſo as the Moone changeth his light, ſometimes on the one ſide, and ſometime on the other, according to the aſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e hath to the Sunne, and yet (except it bee by an Eclypſe for a little while) alwayes hath his full light. So the Church of God, vnleſſe it be for a little Eclypſe of perſecution, is alwayes dilated ouer the world, though more manifeſt in one Countrey, then in another; as wee ſee by experience, that the loſſe which the Church hath in <hi>England,</hi> and ſome corners of the earth, is more then reſtored in <hi>Aſia</hi> &amp; <hi>America.</hi> So it was promiſed by the Prophet, ſaying: <hi>Thy Sunne ſhall go downe no more, and thy Moone ſhall not be dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 60. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe our Lord ſhall be vnto thee for an euerlaſting light:</hi> As our Sauiour ſaid: <hi>I am with you all dayes euen</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>to the conſummation of the world.</hi> And this was the promiſe of God to <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſaying: <hi>His ſeed ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. 37.</note> 
                     <hi>for euer: and his Throne as the Sunne in my ſight, and as the Moone perfect for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 5. Our Sauiour calleth his Church little flocke, ſaying: <hi>Doe not feare little flocke, becauſe it</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</note>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:16729:34"/> 
                     <hi>hath pleaſed your Father to giue you a Kingdome.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Little in the beginning, after to encreaſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the words of the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 27. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall floriſh, and Iſrael ſhall grow, and they ſhall fill the face of the earth with ſeed.</hi> So our Sauiour compared <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 31.</note> his Church to a Muſtard-ſeed, which is the leaſt of all ſeedes when it is ſowen, but when it is growne, it is greater then all herbes: And to Leauen, which a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 33.</note> tooke, and hid in three meaſures of meale, vntill the whole was leauened.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 6. In the time of <hi>Conſtans, Conſtantius,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> the <hi>Arians</hi> ſo preuailed, that there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned no Catholike Biſhops, but <hi>Liberius</hi> and <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> In their times was the Councell of <hi>Sardis,</hi> where were three hundred Catholike Biſhops, as is ſet downe in the ſaid Councell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 7. Our Sauiour ſaith, That <hi>many are called,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>but few choſen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. He hath called the earth, from the riſing of the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Sunne, vnto the going downe thereof.</hi> So in reſpect of the number of all people, of what ſect or ſort ſoeuer, the Elect ſhalbe but few, yet dilated all ouer the earth, as our Sauiour witneſſeth, when he ſaith; That at the day of Iudgement, <hi>he will ſend his Angels with a great</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>ſound of Trumpet, and they ſhall gather his Elect from the foure windes, from the one end of the heauen to the other.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 8. Our Sauiour ſaith of the Iewes, <hi>I know</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 8,</note> 
                     <hi>that you are</hi> Abrahams <hi>ſeed,</hi> and yet, ſaith, <hi>Yee are of your father the Diuell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> This place demonſtrateth, that men are not iuſtified by Faith only, ſhewing that neither the Iews, who were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed by carnall generation, nor the Chriſtians, who are his ſeed by Faith onely, ſhalbe ſaued without good workes, ſaying: <hi>I know you are</hi>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:16729:35"/> Abrahams <hi>ſeed, but yee ſeeke to kill me,</hi> therefore <hi>yee are</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>of your father the Diuell,</hi> begotten of him by euill life: Catholikes doe not defend ſaluation by Faith onely, but by Faith and good deeds.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 9. Some of the Fathers doe vnderſtand by <hi>Babylon</hi> (ſpoken in the 17. of the <hi>Apocalyps) Rome.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apocal.</hi> 17.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. Tertullian, lib. contr. Iudeos,</hi> and Saint <hi>Ierome Epiſt.</hi> 17. <hi>ad Marcellum,</hi> vnderſtand by <hi>Babylon, Rome,</hi> as it perſecuted Chriſtians, and worſhipped Idols, and not <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vpon the 26. Pſalme, <hi>Aretas</hi> vpon this place, <hi>Haymon</hi> and Saint <hi>Bede</hi> do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the great Whore, great <hi>Babylon,</hi> &amp;c. not <hi>Rome:</hi> but the vniuerſall Citie of the Diuell, which in Scriptures is called <hi>Babylon,</hi> and is oppoſite to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God, which is his Church: and by the ſeuen Hills, theſe Fathers vnderſtand the generall eſtate of proud men, as the Scriptures vſe, ſaying: <hi>Euery <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ally</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhal be filled, and euery Hill ſhal be humbled.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 10. In our <hi>Creede</hi> we ſay, <hi>I beleeue in the Catholike Church:</hi> but the things that wee beleeue, cannot be ſeene: therefore wee cannot ſee the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, but muſt beleeue it onely.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Herein conſiſteth the ignorance of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that in one and the ſame thing, they diſtinguiſh diuers acts, as the act of Faith, and the act of corporall ſeeing, both in one and the ſame man: but doe not diſtinguiſh in the ſame men or things, diuers obiects, as the obiect of the act of Faith, and the obiect of the act of corporall ſeeing. So the things that we beleeue, we cannot corporally ſee by an acte of Faith; that is true, otherwiſe our Faith ſhould be in our eyes. The thing that we beleeue, we cannot corporally ſee with an act of ſeeing, that is falſe: the Apoſtles did both ſee and heare our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and beleeued him to bee our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus</hi>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:16729:35"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Catholikes can corporally ſee the Catholike Church, but not with an act of Faith proceeding from their eyes: and beleeue the ſame Catholike Church, but not with an act of ſeeing, proceeding from their vnderſtandings, but with an act of Faith proceeding from their vnderſtandings, and ſo at the ſame time, though not with one and the ſelfe-ſame act, both ſee and beleeue the ſame Catholike Church. But ſee it, as it is obiect of their eyes, and beleeue it, as it is obiect of their Faith, which for the ſaluation of their ſoules, I wiſh Proteſtants could doe: Since the ſame God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and the ſame Prophets which tell me, I muſt beleeue the Church, doe alſo tell me, that it ſhall be corporally viſible, according to their deſcriptions, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the worlds end; and he maketh God and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets lyars that denyeth it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 11. The Proteſtants yet may hope, that the Prophecies may be verified vpon Proteſtantiſme here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That were to make <hi>Luther</hi> the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and him, and his Miniſters of greater power, then our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and the Apoſtles, and is contrary to the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God and Prophecies. Againe, the Prophets do not ſpeake of conuerting Papiſts, but Gentiles to our Lord; which are in great part conuerted already, and there is no probability that Miniſters, tyed to women, children, ſeruants, good fare, ſoft beds, commodities of the world, and fleſh, ſhould goe to conuert Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles in <hi>Africa,</hi> or <hi>America.</hi> Againe, What ſhould they conuert them vnto? to beleeue:</p>
                  <p>That the God of the Chriſtians hath for fifteene hundred yeares failed of his oath and promiſes.</p>
                  <p>That the Apoſtles, and thoſe men who planted Chriſtian Religion, are not to be called, nor eſteemed of as Saints.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:16729:36"/>
                  <p> That Baptiſme is not neceſſarie to ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>That the Sacraments of the Chriſtians doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre grace.</p>
                  <p>That the whole Church, and Generall Councels of Chriſtians may erre, in things that appertaine to God.</p>
                  <p>That Faſting and Pennance is not neceſſarie to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Maſſe</hi> is ſuperſtition.</p>
                  <p>That the Romiſh doctrine concerning Purgatorie, Pardons, Worſhipping and Adoration, as well of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as of Reliques, and alſo Inuocation of Chriſtian Saints is a fond thing.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and many the like Articles of the Engliſh Creed, the Heathen and Pagans beleeue, and haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued many hundred years, before <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> or any Proteſtant man was borne, that held and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſame Faith Proteſtants doe now.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 12. The Church of Proteſtants is farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and ſo, in ſome part, the Prophecies may bee verified vpon it.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though it were as farre extended, as Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme, yet it would bee inferious to the promiſes, and latitude of our Catholike Church, and wanteth the other properties, ſet downe by the Prophets, all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes haue poſſeſſed ſome place or Countrey, and at this day Proteſtantiſme is but in this corner of the world. <hi>Thomas Rogers,</hi> a Proteſtant, ſeeking out the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rogers</hi> vpon the Creede.</note> Proteſtants of other Countries, can find, as it ſeemeth, none to name, but <hi>Suitzerland, Baſil, Bohemia, Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge, Flanders, Saxonie, Sueuia, Wittenberge, France,</hi> yet in <hi>France</hi> there are ten Catholikes for one Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; in <hi>Suitzerland,</hi> ſix Cantons or Prouinces of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes; in <hi>Bohemia</hi> many Catholikes; <hi>Ausburge</hi> but one Citie; <hi>Wittenberge</hi> a Citie; and theſe are but a heap of diuers Sects, whereof the chiefe are Caluiniſts,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16729:36"/> Lutherans, and Engliſh Parliamentary Proteſtants. The Caluiniſts, who are moſt in number, deny the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie of Kings, and authority of Biſhops, which is Treaſon amongſt the Engliſh Proteſtants; the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans hold Conſubſtantiation in their Communion, and deny the Communion of both Caluiniſts and Engliſh Proteſtants, and they both the Communion of Lutherans, all of them eſteeming their Communion a Sacrament, and matter of Faith. Many more Sectes there are amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Anabaptiſts, Huſſites, Arians, Browniſts, Family of Loue, Thraſquites, and others.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="object">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Octiect.</hi> 13. In time of <hi>Elias</hi> there was no viſible Church, <hi>Elias</hi> ſaying, <hi>I alone am left:</hi> therefore the <note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note> Church may decay and become inuiſible.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> When <hi>Elias</hi> ſpoke thoſe words of lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there were two Kingdomes of the Iewes, the one knowne, and called by the name of <hi>Iuda;</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther called and knowne by the name of the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> ouer <hi>Iuda</hi> at this time reigned <hi>Aſa</hi> a good King; ASA <hi>did right before the ſight of our Lord, as</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note> DAVID <hi>his Father did:</hi> ouer <hi>Iſrael</hi> reigned ACHAB, a wicked King, <hi>And</hi> ACHAB <hi>did euill in the ſight of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note> 
                     <hi>our Lord, aboue all that were before him.</hi> ELIAS ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not of <hi>Iuda,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The Children of Iſrael haue forſaken thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note> &amp;c. And our Lord ſaid to him: <hi>I haue left me in Iſrael ſeuen thouſand men, whoſe knees haue not bowed before</hi> BAAL: of whom, at that time it ſeemeth <hi>Elias</hi> knew not of. So in the time of <hi>Elias,</hi> the Church was ſo farre off from being inuiſible, that beſides the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thouſand in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there was the whole viſible Kingdome of <hi>Iuda,</hi> vnder <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Ioſephat</hi> his ſonne, who was likewiſe a good King: IOSEPHAT <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.</note> 
                     <hi>in the way of</hi> ASA <hi>his Father, and he did that which was right in the ſight of our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="object">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:16729:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 14. I haue, ſaith the Puritan, a true feeling of the Spirit, and am aſſured to be ſaued, all others may erre, I am aſſured I cannot, for my ſpirit doth tell me that I am in the right way of ſaluation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw. The way of a foole</hi> (ſaith the holy Ghoſt) <hi>is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 12. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>right in his owne eyes.</hi> I deſire thee to conſider what a miſery it is to be obſtinate in opinion, ſince it maketh a man to vſe all the meanes and ſhifts he can to get to hell, and doth not giue leaue either to reaſon, or to the ſences, to execute their functions: God Almighty hath promiſed that the Chriſtians <hi>ſhall be as the Stars of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.</note> 
                     <hi>and as the ſand that is by the ſea ſhore, and that they ſhall poſſeſſe the gates of their enemies, the mountaines ſhal be moued, and the hils ſhal tremble, but his mercy ſhal not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 54.</note> 
                     <hi>depart from them, and the couenant of his peace with them ſhal not be moued.</hi> According to Gods promiſe, ſuch a ſeed, or ſucceſſion of Chriſtians, wee ſee, Writings, Regiſters, Chronicles, Antiquities, Churches, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, the report and traditions of our Parents, al ſpake it, our Aduerſaries themſelues confeſſe it, experience doth teach vs that it muſt be ſo: All ſeeing it fulfilled from <hi>Abraham,</hi> vntill the Natiuitie of our Sauiour, for one thouſand nine hundred yeares, or thereabouts, yet rather then the obſtinate man will yeeld to ſo manifeſt a truth, and ſaue his ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he will ſeeke out all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, malice, ſhifts, tricks and doubts that can be to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it, and go to Hell: and if none will ſerue to cloake his obſtinacie, yet rather then hee will change his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he will go on, he will not beleeue any thing but his owne fantaſies and imaginations: All others may be deceiued, he is ſure he cannot. O be not obſtinate, but haue pity on thy poore ſoule; Was thou neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in any thing in all thy life, whereof thou eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medſt thy ſelfe ſure? certainly thou haſt. And if thou wilt not bee an Ethnicke and Publican to thy owne
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16729:37"/> Congregation of Proteſtants, thou muſt defend, that nothing is more certaine, then that the Church of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants millitant and viſible may erre, as is affirmed in the Engliſh Creed, <hi>Art.</hi> 19. <hi>prop.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; Art.</hi> 21. So if thou beeſt not already gotten into heauen, into a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Church, and art become an inuiſible man, in thy owne militant Church, there is nothing more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, then that thou mayeſt erre. Well then, thou mayeſt be deceiued in this; that thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe ſo ſure of. Thou wilt grant mee this principle, that God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie can neither deceiue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor be deceiued; ſince he is veritie it ſelfe, and the firſt cauſe: ſo if hee affirme one thing, and thou, and <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> deny the ſelfe-ſame thing, yet that muſt be true which God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty affirmeth, and that falſe you affirme: Thou wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt not deny this? But God Almighty affirmeth that the Chriſtians, the Seede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the people of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.</note> God, ſhould be multiplied as the Starres of heauen, and as the ſand which is by the ſea ſhore, and ſhould poſſeſſe the gates of their enemies, and bee dilated to the Eaſt, and to the Weſt, and to the North, and to the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.</note> South for euer. Well then, it muſt be true, though thou <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55.</note> 
                     <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> deny it. But thou wilt ſay, theſe promiſes are not made to Chriſtians: Againe, whom ſhall we beleeue in this, God Almighty, or thou, or <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Caluin?</hi> God Almighty affirmeth, that theſe oathes and promiſes of God are to bee fulfilled vpon the Chriſtians, ſaying: <hi>All things muſt needs be fulfilled</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 44.</note> 
                     <hi>which are written in the Law of</hi> Moyſes, <hi>and the Prophets and Pſalmes of mee.</hi> And the like affirme the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as we haue ſet downe at large in the eleuenth and twelfth Chapter.</p>
                  <p>So if thou wilt not, according to thy owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, bee wilfully deceiued, thou muſt beleeue, that there muſt be Chriſtians, the people of God, the Seed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16729:38"/> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> embracing one and the ſame Faith, <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied as the Stars of heauen, and as the ſand that is by the ſea ſhore, dilated to the Eaſt, and to the Weſt, to the North, and to the South, poſſeſſing the gates of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: As he ſpake to our Fathers, to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55.</note> 
                     <hi>Seed for euer.</hi> And if thou doeſt not beleeue this, thou muſt confeſſe, that, that thou art ſo farre off from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Seed of the Faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> that thou doeſt not beleeue the promiſe which God Almightie made vnto him, and ſo mayeſt manifeſtly ſee thy owne infidelitie.</p>
                  <p>And this ſecond principle ſuppoſed to be a diuine truth, as now thou confeſſeſt: Art not thou againe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blinde, that will not ſee thoſe Chriſtians, the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the people of God, to be the Catholikes, whom thou calleſt Papiſts? ſince at this day there are no Chriſtians, vpon whom this promiſe can be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but vpon them: and as for former ages, thy owne fellow Sectaries confeſſe, that for many hundered yeares, <hi>The Popiſh Hereſie hath ſpread it ſelfe ouer the whole earth,</hi> as is ſet downe in the third Chapter; and ſince for one thouſand foure hundred yeares together, thou art not able to bring forth any writing, teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, antiquitie or euidence of any one Proteſtant Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or Doctor, that held the doctrine Proteſtants now teach: Wilt not thou then obſtinately go to hell, that will be a Proteſtant, and in thy imagination find out them, which haue not bin to the diſhonor of God, and thy damnation? And willeſt not ſee a multitude of men, which are, and haue been as the Stars of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for the ſaluation of thy ſoule, and glory of God, in fulfilling his oathes and promiſes?</p>
                  <p>But thou wilt ſay, that ſuppoſe there were ſuch an infinite number of Chriſtians, the people of God, ſo viſible, as that they poſſeſſed the gates of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16729:38"/> as God Almightie affirmeth: yet I cannot finde ſuch a multitude of men, profeſſing one and the ſame Faith. To which I anſwere, that hereby thou ſhouldeſt moſt manifeſtly ſee that thou art obſtinate: thou wilt confeſſe that all Chriſtians, which euer haue beene, may be comprehended vnder one of theſe three ſorts, knowne Heretikes to both parties, Proteſtants and Papiſts: knowne Heretikes on both parties, thou wilt confeſſe, not to haue been this ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants thou canſt not aſſigne one, that taught, and held the doctrine thou now holdeſt, in all them one thouſand foure hundred yeares. See now if thou beeſt not obſtinate, that will not know that the ſeede of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> were the Papiſts: when it is ſo manifeſt, that reputed Heretikes to both parties excepted, for one thouſand foure hundred yeares together, thou canſt finde none elſe.</p>
                  <p>Againe, knowne and reputed Heretikes, thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeſt to haue bin amongſt the Chriſtians, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of them one thouſand foure hundred yeares; but they were not knowne, or reputed ſuch in theſe ages by Proteſtants, who then were not; but by Papiſts, who both ſpied them out, and ouercame them, according to theſe Prophecies: So art not thou obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, that doeſt not ſee the Prophecies verified vpon the Papiſts?</p>
                  <p>Againe, all the Chriſtian Kings and Kingdomes (knowne Heretikes on both ſides excepted) as their Hiſtories, Chronicles, Lawes, Antiquities, reports of Parents doe teſtifie, were Papiſts: then art not thou obſtinat that will not ſee the Prophecies to be verified vpon Papiſts?</p>
                  <p>But thou wilt ſay that the Papiſts Church hath fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; but ſo ſhould not the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> To which I anſwere, that God Almightie affirmed that his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16729:39"/> Church, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſhould not faile, and cannot be contrary to himſelfe; and thou findeſt no other congregation of men, which euen in thy owne judgment, hath longer endured according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of the Prophets, then the Papiſts, euen admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the worſt thou ſayeſt of it: ſo if thou wilt not bee obſtinate, and fall into Atheiſme, thou ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; certainly it is falſe that the Papiſts Church hath failed: for when thou ſayeſt that the Church of Papiſts fell; thou canſt not ſay that it fell to Proteſtantiſme, ſo it maketh nothing for thee, vnleſſe thou wouldeſt be an Atheiſt, and proue that God Almighty hath vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated his oathes and promiſes; and go againſt the firſt principle, and ſay that God may be deceiued, but man cannot; and likewiſe againſt the ſecond principle, and ſay there were no knowne Chriſtians of the ſeede of <hi>Abraham</hi> vpon earth, for many hundred yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If thou beeſt a creature of God Almighties, thou art firſt bound to maintaine his honor and glory, and ſhew vpon what Chriſtians his promiſes are fulfilled, and then thine owne, otherwiſe thou makeſt thy ſelfe an Idoll, and denyeſt God. So firſt ſhew vs Proteſtants multiplied as the Stars of heauen, and as the ſand that is by the ſea ſhore, dilated to the Eaſt, to the Weſt, to the North, and to the South, which poſſeſſed the gates of their enemies; and then ſhew vs, when and where the Papiſts Church decayed, and what Religion they embraced, when they fell from Papiſtrie.</p>
                  <p>That it did decay, thou alledgeſt the authoritie of ſome few; that it did not decay, I bring thee the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Scriptures, and the generall conſent of all knowne Chriſtians, for one thouſand foure hundred yeares together (knowne Heretikes, and ſo reputed on both parties, onely excepted) as is ſet downe in the firſt, ſecond, and third Chapters. So if any reaſon may
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16729:39"/> preuaile with thee, thou muſt needs confeſſe, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are the Seede and children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that our Lord by the teſtimony of the Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and himſelfe, planted that Religion Proteſtants call Papiſtrie.</p>
                  <p>Neither mayeſt thou object that the teſtimonies of the Prophets, concerning our Sauiour and his Church, are obſcure, and their meaning hard to be found out; when God Almightie affirmeth by the mouth of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> That they are <hi>as a candle ſhining in a darke place,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19.</note> into which, if thou doeſt but looke, and not obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhut thy eyes, thou mayeſt ſee light: So open thy eyes, and accommodate thy vnderſtanding to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and beleeue firmely, that to be the true Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which hath been ſpread ouer the earth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeares, according to the Prophecies, &amp; do not accommodate the Prophets to thy vnderſtanding: take not for a firſt ground, that thy ſect is true, and then ſeeke to ſhape the ſayings of the Prophets to thy vnderſtdanding, and to thy ſect, ſo thou ſhalt make thy ſelfe an Idoll, and be alwayes blinde, vntill thou fall into euerlaſting darkneſſe, and there lamenting, ſay; <hi>We haue groaped as blinde men for the wall; and as</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 59.</note> 
                     <hi>without eyes haue feeled, we haue ſtumbled at none day, as in darkneſſe, in darke places as the dead,</hi> that could not ſee the Seede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Church of Chriſt, a multitude of men, which held one and the ſame Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith vpon earth, without preuaricating in ſenſe, when euen in our dayes; <hi>they were multiplied as</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>the Starres of heauen, and as the ſand that is by the ſea ſhore, dilated to the Eaſt, and to the Weſt, and to the North, and to the South</hi> (in Europe, Aſia, Affrica, and America) <hi>ouerflowing the glory of the Gentiles, and being a light and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.</note> 
                     <hi>ſaluation to the furthest parts of the earth, who had Kings their nurſing fathers, and Queenes their nurſes, who with</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:16729:40"/> 
                     <hi>countenance caſt downe to the ground adored them, and kiſſed their feete: Deſarts as delicaſies, and wilderneſſes</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 51.</note> wherein liued contemplatiue men, as <hi>the gardens of our Lord, vpon whoſe walles ſtood watchmen day and night, holding not their peace,</hi> keeping the Quier in one place or other perpetually: <hi>Wee ſenceleſſe, eſteemed their life</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 5. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>madneſſe, and their end without honor. Behold how they are counted among the children of God, and their lot is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Saints. We therefore haue erred from the way of truth, and the light of Iuſtice hath not ſhined to vs. Such things ſaid they in Hell which ſinned.</hi> And I ſet it downe for thy example, that yet whileſt there is time, thou mayeſt become one of the Seede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and be partaker of his bleſſings, which with all my heart I wiſh vnto thee, and all Proteſtants, and Puritans.</p>
                  <p>Thus hauing abundantly ſhewed vnto your moſt excellent <hi>Maieſty,</hi> that our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> was Author of the Catholike Roman Faith: It reſteth to ſet downe, who was Author of the Faith and Religion now publikely profeſſed in England by Proteſtant Miniſters.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Queene</hi> ELIZABETH <hi>was Author of the Faith and Religion publikely now profeſſed in England, and vpon what occaſion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> together with the Crowne, after the death of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> belonging by all Law and right, vnto your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as lineally deſcended from <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth <hi>(Henry</hi> the eights lawfull Line being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16729:40"/> in Queene <hi>Mary):</hi> to the great prejudice of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Mother, Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> tooke vpon her the Crown; and knowing, that not only of all Catholikes, ſhee was eſteemed Illigitimate, and for ſuch publiſhed by the Church of God, planted by our Sauior, for that ſhee was borne of <hi>Anne Boloigne,</hi> during the life time of the firſt wife of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, her ſuppoſed Father; but alſo by a Decree in publike Parliament, holden in the eight and twentith yeare of the Reigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, her ſuppoſed Father: <hi>Shee was</hi> (to vſe the words of the Statute) <hi>iudged Illigitimate, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and barred to claime, challenge, or demand any Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, as lawfull Heire to</hi> Henry <hi>the eight;</hi> as remaineth yet to bee ſeene amongſt the Statutes of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, printed by <hi>Thomas Berthlet,</hi> the Kings Printer, and ſet forth with Priuiledge.</p>
               <p>And fearing, leſt for the ſaid cauſe of Illigitimation, her Subjects ſhould forſake her, and ſtand to the right Heire, your Mother, or that Chriſtian Kings would not permit ſo euill a preſident, in prejudice of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lineall diſcent of Kings: caſting off all feare of God, ſhee reſolued, at what price ſoeuer to reigne, and to that end beganne to practiſe <hi>Ieroboams</hi> policie, of whom it is written, that hauing obtained a part of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi> Kingdome, <hi>Thought in his heart, now will the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Kingdome returne to the Houſe of</hi> Dauid. <hi>If this people ſhall go vp to make Sacrifice in the houſe of our Lord, into Ieruſalem, the heart of this people will be turned to their Lord</hi> Roboam, <hi>the King of Iuda, and they will kill me, and returne to him: and finding out a deuice, he made two gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calfes, and ſaid to them, Go vp no more into Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: Behold thy Gods, Iſrael, which brought thee out of the Land of Aegypt: And he put one in</hi> Bethel, <hi>and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Parap.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>in</hi> Dan. <hi>And he made Prieſts of the obiects of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which were not of the Tribe of</hi> Leui, <hi>and caſt off the</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:16729:41"/> 
                  <hi>Prieſts and Leuites, that were in all Iſrael, and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, that they ſhould not execute the Prieſt-hood of our Lord.</hi> And by theſe meanes <hi>Ieroboam</hi> eſteemed, though falſely to eſtabliſh the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in him, and his Poſteritie.</p>
               <p>So Ladie <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being thus aſcended to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the Law of God, Nature, and Nations, fearing leſt her Subjects ſhould forſake Her, and adhere vnto Your Mother, the lawful Heire (if they continued in the Catholike Faith, with Your Mother, and other people, and Kingdomes) ſhee put in practiſe this <hi>Ieroboams</hi> wicked policie, and Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſered al the Catholike Prieſts and Biſhops in this Land and their Poſteritie, that they ſhould not execute the Prieſt-hood of our Lord, and vnder a veile of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Gouernour, ſhee tooke vpon her all ſpirituall Power and Authoritie, and would not admit any to be Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Miniſter, who would not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure and renounce all authoritie deriued from <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> the Sonne of God, and his Apoſtles, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue all their Power, Spirituall Authoritie, and Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction from her a woman: So that none could in her time be made an Archbiſhop, Biſhop, Miniſter or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, or receiue any Degree in Schooles, or beare any Office vnder her, but he muſt firſt take the oath of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renunciation, of all power and authoritie, which was not deriued from Her, as followeth.</p>
               <p>I. A. B. <hi>Doe vtterly teſtifie, and declare in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. An.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Queenes Highneſſe is the onely Supreame Gouernour of this Realme, and of all other Her Highneſſe Dominions and Countries, as well in all Spirituall, or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall things, or cauſes, as Temporall, and that no forraine Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate</hi> (ſuch as were our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who were borne in <hi>Iuda,</hi> or thereabouts) <hi>hath</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:16729:41"/> 
                  <hi>or ought to haue any Iuriſdiction, Power, Superiorite, Preheminence or Authoritie Eccleſiaſticall or Spirituall, within this Realme, and therefore I doe vtterly renounce and forſake all forraine Iuriſdiction, Powers, Superiorities and Authorities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if any did refuſe to take the ſaid oath of Abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of all forraine Authoritie, ſuch as was the Authoritie deriued from our Sauiour and the Apoſtles, and deny her Supreame Spirituall Authoritie in all things, they ſhould neither beare Office, nor be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any Degree in Schooles, or bee made Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Miniſters, Deacons, as is ſet downe at large in the firſt Chapter of the ſaid Statute made in the firſt yeare of her reigne. And that there ſhould be in her time no perſon or perſons, or man whoſoeuer, that might challenge any authoritie from <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> or the Apoſtles; but that all Spirituall Power, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, might be wholly in her, and receiued from her: Shee made a Law in her ſaid firſt Parliament, <hi>That no forraine Prince, Perſon, Prelate,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. An.</hi> 1. <hi>El. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>State or Potentate Spirituall or Temporall, ſhal after the laſt day of this Seſſion of Parliament, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, enioy or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any manner of Power, Iuriſdiction, Superiority, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Preheminence or Priuiledge, Spirituall or Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, within this Realme, or within any of her Maieſties dominions, or Countries that now be, or hereafter ſhal be, but from henceforth the ſame ſhalbe clearely aboliſhed out of this Realme, and all other your Highneſſe Dominions for euer: any Statute, Ordinance, Cuſtome, Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or any other matter, or cauſe whatſoeuer to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which Law, ſhee hath not onely aboliſhed out of this Realme, all the Authority which the Sonne of God left vpon earth, but alſo as much as lyeth in her power, ſhee hath debarred him from comming to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16729:42"/> Iudgement within her Dominions, or ſending any one hither to preach or teach, that all authoritie might bee in her ſelfe, and come from her, to her Subjects, as from their God, or golden Calfe, vpon earth.</p>
               <p>And leſt there might be ſome doubt, how far her womanly Supreame-headſhip, in all things, might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, ſhee made another Law, to make it as large, as euer was the authoritie of our Lord, or his Apoſtles vpon earth; ſaying in the aforeſaid Parliament: Be it enacted by the authoritie aforeſaid; <hi>That ſuch iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. An.</hi> 1. <hi>El. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>priuiledges, ſuperiorities, and preheminences, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Eccleſiaſtical, as by any Spiritual, or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal power, or authoritie, hath heretofore been, or may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be exerciſed or vſed, for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical State and perſons, and for reformation, order, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the ſame, and of al manner errors, hereſies, ſchiſmes, abuſes, offences, contempts and enormities, ſhal for euer, by authority of this preſent Parliament, be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and annexed to the Imperial Crowne of this Realme.</hi> That being crowned Queene, though a woman, and a Baſtard; yet now ſhee might haue as large Spirituall authoritie, as any man euer had, or might haue.</p>
               <p>And ſo ſhee tranſlated the Spirituall authoritie of Prieſthood, not only from Spirituall to Temporall, but alſo from male vnto female, that whatſoeuer Spirituall or Eccleſiaſticall power or authoritie, hath heretofore been, or may be lawfully vſed or exerciſed, for the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of the Eccleſiaſticall State and perſons, and reformation and giuing of orders, and for the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them, and all manner of errors, hereſies, ſchiſmes, abuſes, offences, was by this law ſuppoſed to be who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in her a woman. And executing her Supreame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Function, in the firſt yeares of her raigne, ſhee ſet out two and fiftie Injunctions, vnder title of the Queenes Injunctions, with this Concluſion annexed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16729:42"/> to them. <hi>All which and ſingular Iniunctions, the Queenes Maieſtie miniſtreth vnto her Clergie, and to al her louing Subiects, ſtraitly charging and commanding them to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and keepe the ſame, vnder paine of deprauation, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration of fruits and Benefices, ſuspenſion, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and other ſuch coherſion of Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by this meanes, ſhee had all the Clergie at her command, both the enjoying of their Temporall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, and Spirituall Offices, depending wholly vpon her feminine authoritie. In ſo much as, in the firſt yeare of her raigne, there ariſing ſome doubts about the lawfull making of her Archbiſhops, and Biſhops; ſhe by her effeminate authoritie, diſpenſed with all their diſabilities, in theſe words: <hi>Her Highneſſe by her Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. An.</hi> 5. <hi>El. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>power, hath diſpenſed with all cauſes or doubts of any diſability,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>about the making of the ſaid Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops and Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that no cauſe or ſcruple, ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or doubt, can or may be iuſtly obiected againſt the ſaid Elections, Confirmations, or Conſecration.</hi> And in the eight yeare of her raigne, doubts ariſing againe about the Conſecration and making of her Archbiſhops and Biſhops, ſhe ſignifieth her former diſpenſation, ſaying; <hi>For as much as diuers queſtions hath lately growen, about</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. An.</hi> 8. <hi>El. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>the making and conſecrating of Archbiſhops and Biſhops within this Realme,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Her Highneſſe by her Supreame power and authoritie, hath diſpenſed with al cauſes or doubts of any imperfection or diſabilitie, that can or may any wiſe be obiected againſt the ſame.</hi> And in the nine and thirtith yeare of her reigne, yet ſome doubts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining amongſt her Subiects, that the Catholike Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, whom ſhee out of her effeminate authority had depriued, were lawfull Biſhops, and hers falſe: ſhee depriued the Catholike Biſhoppes againe, and made their authoritie void, to all intents and purpoſes, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16729:43"/> by her Law; <hi>That al and euery depriuation, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. An.</hi> 39. <hi>El. Cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>depriuations, and al euery ſentence, and ſentences of depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation whatſoeuer, had, pronounced, or giuen, at any time betweene the beginning of the reigne of the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſty that now is, and the tenth of Nouember in the fourth yeare of the ſame, (againſt any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which was, or tooke vpon him to be Archbiſhop, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of any Sea, or Biſhopricke, or Deane of any Deanery, within this Realme, or any the Dominion thereof, in the reigne of the ſaid late Queene</hi> Mary, <hi>from ſuch Sea or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke) be adiudged, deemed, and taken good, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in Law to all intents and purpoſes, and ſo ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine and continue, any appeale, exception, or other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or thing whatſoeuer to the contrary thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding: And that al ſuch Archbiſhops, and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>and Deanes as were ordained, or made, by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or licence of the Queenes Maieſty that now is, at any time betweene the beginning of her reigne, and the ſaid tenth day of Nouember, in the fourth yeare of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties reigne, ſhalbe taken and adiudged to be lawful Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, or Biſhop of the Sea or Biſhopricke, and Deane of the Deanery, vnto the which he was ſo preferred, aſſigned or appointed: And that the ſame Sea of Archbiſhop or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke and Deanery, vnto the which he was ſo preferred, aſſigned or appointed</hi> (though there were in it a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Biſhop, as they were all in the beginning of her reigne, yet it) <hi>ſhalbe deemed, and adiudged to be meerely void to all reſpects and purpoſes,</hi> &amp;c. And by this means, as much as lay in her, ſhee depriued all the ancient Archbiſhops and Biſhops, both of their Spirituall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, and Temporall Biſhoprickes, to all intents and purpoſes, and admitted and eſtabliſhed theſe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who, whereas the Statute ſaith, <hi>ordained, or made by the authority of the Queene:</hi> and allowed, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of no authoritie, Spirituall or Eccleſiaſticall,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16729:43"/> but in her and from her deriued to them. In ſo much as <hi>Fulke,</hi> glorying in the Spirituall influence he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from this Illigitimate Lady, in his Anſwere to a Counterfeit Catholike, pag. 50. ſaith to Catholikes, <hi>You are vtterly deceiued, if you thinke your Offices of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, any better then Lay-men; and you preſume too much, to thinke that we receiue your or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining to be lawfull.</hi> And in his Retentiue Motiues, pag. 67. he ſaith; <hi>With all our hearts, we defie, abhorre, deteſt, and ſpit at, your ſtinking, greaſie Antichriſtian Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> And WHITAKER <hi>cont. Durem, lib.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 821. ſaith; <hi>I would not haue you to thinke we make ſuch recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your Orders, as to make our owne vocation vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full without them, and therefore keepe them to your ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all the Spirituall or Eccleſiaſticall power, which any Archbiſhop, Biſhop or Miniſter, hath ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to teach, preach, adminiſter Sacraments, or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Miniſters, together with any right, which they can pretend to any Archbiſhopricke, Biſhopricke, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, &amp;c. doth ſo fully and wholly depend vpon Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her womanly authoritie, and Statutes made by her, that her femall Supreme Spirituall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Statutes repealed, all the Archbiſhoprickes, Biſhopricks, and Parſonages within this Realme, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Offices, are voyde in Law, and as void, reſt to be diſpoſed. So that no other can, or may bee juſtly ſaid, to be the Author and Founder of that Faith and Religion, which is now by publike authority pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in <hi>England,</hi> but onely Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for that from her, the Engliſh Proteſtant Archbiſhops, Biſhops and Miniſters, had whatſoeuer Prieſthood, or Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all authority they can, or may pretend, or challenge, either to adminiſter Sacraments, Teach or Preach, or execute any other ſpiritual ſuppoſed function: neither can Engliſh Proteſtant Miniſters deny it, vnleſſe they
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16729:44"/> deny the Queenes Supremacie, and proclaime them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be perjured in the oath of Supremacie, which they haue ſworne. Whereupon they are juſtly and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Elizabethians,</hi> and ought not, nor ſhould not be called by any other name, ſeeing they haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Author, or Founder of their Religion and Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, but Queene ELIZABETH, as we haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by publike Statutes.</p>
               <p>And this Queene ELIZABETH did, not that ſhee did thinke, that ſhe being a woman had Supreme authoritie in all Spirituall <hi>things, or cauſes,</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſaying: <hi>Let women hold their peace in the Church,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>for it is not permitted them to ſpeake, but to be ſubiect.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>It is a filthy thing for a woman to ſpeake in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Church.</hi> Againe, <hi>Let women learne in ſilence, with all ſubiection, for I doe not permit a woman to teach.</hi> But de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> to reigne in this world, with whatſoeuer diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of God, and danger ſoeuer of loſing of her ſoule, and damnation of her Subiects, ſhee tooke vpon her IEROBOAMS <hi>Policies,</hi> to ſtrengthen her ſelfe againſt Your Mother.</p>
               <p>So I appeale vnto your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> well pleaſed to conſider the wrong, and injuſtice your Proteſtant Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters doe vnto vs Roman Catholikes, your ancient Subjects, in perſecuting vs, with the loſſe of goods, lands, libertie and life, for that we will not forſake the Religion planted vpon earth by the Sonne of <hi>God,</hi> to profeſſe in place thereof, a Policie inuented by an Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:16729:44"/>
               <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND for Concluſion, I humbly beſeech your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> well pleaſed to conſider, that without a true Faith <hi>it is impoſible</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. 6. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>to pleaſe God.</hi> Againe, <hi>He that doth not beleeue</hi> (the Faith planted by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>is already iudged.</hi> And the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, <hi>Get yee away from me yee accurſed into fire euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>which was prepared for the Diuell and his angels.</hi> And preſently after this ſentence giuen, they are caſt into Hell; which is as the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaith: <hi>A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and ſpacious roome, his food is fire and ſtore of wood, the breath of our Lords mouth doth kindle the ſame, like a maine Riuer of Brimſtone:</hi> and there bound hands and feete, they are placed in a bed of Moathes, to gnawe perpetually on their carkaſſes; and in ſcorne of the pride of life, in which they liued vpon earth, couered with a couering of Lice; as the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſaying: <hi>Thy pride is drawne down into Hell, thy car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>is fallen, the moath ſhalbe ſtrowen vnder thee, and wormes ſhalbe thy couering.</hi> And placed in this wofull and lamentable eſtate, they are deliuered vp into the hands of Diuels, who as miniſters of Gods wrath, power out vpon them, <hi>Fire, haile, famine, death, teeth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 39. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>of beaſts, ſcorpions, and ſerpents. And the ſmoake of their torments ſhall aſcend vp for euer and euer.</hi> Without any hope of eaſe, or any poſſibilitie for one moment, euer to haue their torments leſſened, for that they ſhall bee for euer the ſame, as the Prophet ſaith; <hi>He loued cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.</note> 
                  <hi>and it ſhal come to him, and he would not bleſſing</hi> (that with which God hath bleſſed all Nations of the earth, according to his promiſe) <hi>and it ſhalbe far from him,</hi> in all eternitie he ſhall neither heare, or haue any: which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16729:45"/> conſiderations ought much to moue the heart of your moſt excellent <hi>Maieſty,</hi> to take pity vpon a number of your Subjects, who haue no other Faith or Religion, then that which is grounded vpon the maledictions of God, and out of your compaſſion to reſtore vnto them againe the liberty of embracing the Catholike Roman Faith, which as wee haue aboundantly prooued, was planted vpon earth by our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> the Sonne of God, and there is no ſaluation in any other. And by ſo doing, your <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſhall much honour God, put an end to all new Sectes, eſtabliſh your Throne as the dayes of heauen, bring abundance of peace and quietneſſe to your afflicted Subjects, and as you haue vnited the two Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> in one; ſo you ſhall vnite your ſelfe and them to God, and the reſt of the Chriſtian world, and be partaker of all the bleſſings promiſed to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church.</p>
               <p>The meanes is ſo eaſie, that if your <hi>Maieſty</hi> pleaſe, you may do it without infringing any Law, by diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation out of your Prerogatiue Royall, with all Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes made againſt the Catholike Roman Faith: which Faith not being euill in it ſelfe, but truth and verity, as we haue abundantly proued: the Lawes of the Land giue your <hi>Maieſty</hi> full leaue to diſpence with then all, as is ſet downe in <hi>Termino Michaelis, An.</hi> 11. <hi>Henrici Septimo,</hi> Your moſt worthy Anceſtor, Chap. 35. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The diuerſity betweene</hi> malum prohibitum, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum per ſe malum prohibitum, <hi>is where the Statute doth prohibite, that a man ſhall coyne no money, and if he do, he ſhalbe hanged; this is</hi> malum prohibitum, <hi>for before the ſaid Statute, it was a lawfull act to coyne money, but not after; and for this euill the King may diſpence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Euen ſo, if a man ſhip wooll, for other places then for</hi> Calleis, <hi>this is</hi> malum prohibitum, <hi>for it is prohibited by Statute,</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:16729:45"/> 
                  <hi>and for this euill the King may diſpence,</hi> &amp;c. in like caſe: <hi>But</hi> malum in ſe, <hi>neither the King, nor any other can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence withall, as if the King would pardon to kill another, or giue leaue to robbe vpon the high-way; this is void: yet when they are done, the King may pardon them: So it is, if a man be bound by Recogniſance in the Chancery, to keep the Peace at the ſuite of another man, the King cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe the duetie, for the preiudice which may happen to the other, yet when it is forfeited, he may well releaſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not: and ſo neither King, Biſhop, nor Prieſt can giue leaue to one to commit Lechery, becauſe it is euill,</hi> in ſe, <hi>in the Law of Nature, but when it is done, they may abſolue them very well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Lawes of the Land, giue libertie to the Kings of the Land to diſpence with any thing, which is not euill in it ſelfe, but made euill by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as was the Catholike Roman Faith, in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament holden in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and yourt <hi>Maieſty.</hi> Whereby it is ſufficiently manifeſt, that your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> may out of your prerogatiue Royall, as well, and with as good authoritie diſpence with all penallties impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Statute vpon your Subjects, for profeſſing the Catholike Roman Faith, and giue them free liberty to profeſſe it, as you may diſpence with Merchants freely to tranſport out of the Realme, Siluer, Wooll, or other Merchandize forbidden by Act of Parliament.</p>
               <p>And the reaſons or motiues, which ought to moue, your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> to diſpence with the ſaid Statutes, are as many, and as weightie, as in any caſe can be giuen: whereof I will repeate onely ſome few, out of which others may be collected.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for that the ſaid Statutes are contrary to the honor of God, his oathes, words, and Law, as we haue abundantly prooued throughout this booke, and as
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16729:46"/> your <hi>Maieſty</hi> well affirmeth in your Speech in the Star-chamber, printed 1616. <hi>There is another Law, of all Lawes free and Supreame,</hi> which is <hi>Gods</hi> Law: <hi>And by this all common and municipall Lawes muſt be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: And except they haue dependance vpon this Law, they are vniuſt and vnlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, they defame <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an men, who euer were before the time of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the eight, knowne and reputed Heretikes by both parties onely excepted. For that they all eyther com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or helped, or aſſiſted, or gaue counſell to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe actions, which are by the ſaid Statutes made Treaſon, Fellony, or Criminall, as we haue proued in the firſt, ſecond, and third Chapters.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they are contrary to the ſolemne oathes of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> taken at their Coronation, according to the ancient Lawes and Cuſtomes of this Land, as in the Saxon Law, left by King <hi>Engward</hi> the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lex Sancti Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardi</hi> 7.</note> Confeſſor, it is ſaid: That the King, becauſe he is Gods Vicegerent vpon earth, is ordained <hi>to gouerne his earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kingdome, and people of God, and aboue all things, that hereuerence the holy Church</hi> (which is our <hi>Catholike Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Church, as I haue abundantly proued) <hi>defend her from the iniurious, pull the euil doers from her, and vtterly diſperſe them.</hi> Againe, <hi>The King ought to feare God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al things, and keepe his Commandements through-out the Land: he ought to preſerue the Lands, Honors, Rights, Dignities, and Liberties of the Crowne, and the Rights of the Realme</hi> (ſuch as is eſpecially the Catholike <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, planted in this Land by the Apoſtles) <hi>loſt, diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and waſted, to recall with all his power to their ancient and due eſtate. He ought to ſet vp good Lawes, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued Cuſtomes; and euill Lawes deſtroy, and put from his kingdome,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All which to do, the King in proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to giue an oath, vpon the holy Goſpell, and vpon</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:16729:46"/> 
                  <hi>the bleſſed Reliques, in the preſence of the whole kingdome, the Prieſt-hood, and the Laytie.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Bracton,</hi> an <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bracton, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> ancient Lawyer, ſaith: <hi>The King at his Coronation, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an oath, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, ought to promiſe theſe three to his Subiects.</hi> Firſt, <hi>That he will command, and to his power doe his endeauour, that true peace be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes obſerued to the Church of God, and to all Chriſtian people.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That he ſhould forbid rapine</hi> (ſuch as is the Purſeuants taking away of Catholikes goods, without forme or order of Law) <hi>and all iniquities, to all ſorts of people.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That in all maner of iudgements he command equity, and mercy to be vſed, as he would that our benigne and merciful God ſhould ſhew mercy vnto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to which Law, the Kings of England at their Coronations haue alwaies bin ſolemnely ſworne to defend the Church of God, and her liberties, to ſet vp good Lawes, and deſtroy euill, and doe juſtice, &amp;c. So <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror at his Coronation, <hi>tooke an</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stow</hi> in his life.</note> 
                  <hi>oath on the Altar of S.</hi> Peter, <hi>where he promiſed before the Clergie and all the people, to defend the holy Church of God, the Paſtors thereof, and all the people ſubiect vnto him, he ſhould iuſtly gouerne, he would ordaine good Laws, and obſerue true iuſtice, and to the vttermost of his power to withſtand all rapines, and falſe iudgements.</hi> MAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MESBVRY maketh mention of the oath of King <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> to this effect. In the Records of the <hi>Tower,</hi> in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, and firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, are ſet downe their ſeuerall oathes, to this effect. And your <hi>Maieſty</hi> maketh mention of your oath in your Speech in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> 1616. ſaying: <hi>I proteſt in Gods preſence, my care hath euer been to keepe my conſcience cleare, in all points of my oath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at my Coronation.</hi> Againe in the ſame booke, and leafe, <hi>I haue reſolued to renue my promiſe, and oath made at my Coronation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:16729:47"/>
               <p> Herein your <hi>Maieſty</hi> may bee like <hi>Aſa</hi> the good King of <hi>Iuda,</hi> who at the words of <hi>Azarias</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <note place="margin">2. <hi>Parel.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Tooke away the Idols out of the Land of</hi> Iuda, <hi>and</hi> Beniamin, <hi>and gathered together all</hi> Iuda <hi>and</hi> Beniamin, <hi>and when they were come into Ieruſalem, he went in after the maner to eſtabliſh the couenant, that they ſhould ſeeke our Lord, the God of their Fathers, in all their heart, and in all their ſoule. And if any man, quoth he, ſhal not ſeeke our Lord, the God of Iſrael, let him die, from the leaſt to the greateſt, from man vnto woman. And they ſware to our Lord witb a loud voice, in iubilation, and in noyſe of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and ſound of Shalmes, all that were in</hi> Iuda <hi>with exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, for in all their heart did they ſweare,</hi> the King, and all the people, to ſeeke our Lord, the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his Law, Religion, and Commandements.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, (if we will beleeue the Scriptures) they will be the deſtruction of your Kingdome and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and therefore oblige all thoſe who ſincerely loue your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and your Poſterity, to deſire their abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or diſpenſation. <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid to the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which now we Chriſtians are, <hi>I will teach you</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 12. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>the good and right way. Feare our Lord and ſerue him in truth, and from your whole heart. But if you ſhal perſeuere in malice, both you, and your King ſhal periſh together.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid to SAVL, <hi>Thou haſt not kept the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 13. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Commandements of our Lord thy God, which he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee, which if thou haddeſt done, euen now had our Lord prepared thy kingdome ouer</hi> Iſrael <hi>for euer, but thy kingdome ſhall no further ariſe.</hi> So MOYSES ſaith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>When he ſhall heare the words of this oath</hi> (of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betweene God and man) <hi>he bleſſed himſelfe in his heart, ſaying: I ſhal haue place, and walke in the priuity of my heart,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then</hi> (ſhall) <hi>Gods fury moſt ſpecially fume, and his zeale againſt that man, and all the curſes ſit vpon him, that be written in</hi> Deutronomie, <hi>and our Lord will</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:16729:47"/> 
                  <hi>aboliſh his name vnder heauen.</hi> Which we ſee by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to haue beene verified of late yeares, vpon two of the greateſt Monarkes that were in Chriſtendome, <hi>Henry</hi> the eight King of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>France: Henry</hi> the eight was the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of theſe Statutes: <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond went in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with thirtie thouſand men, to ayde the Proteſtants of <hi>Germany,</hi> as witneſſeth <hi>Serres</hi> in his life: <hi>Henry</hi> the eight had fiue or ſixe wiues, and fiue or ſixe children: and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond had fiue ſonnes, yet we ſee that both their names are aboliſhed from vnder heauen, their Kingdomes or Reignes ended, and not a man of them left to piſſe againſt the wall; according to the words of God.</p>
               <p>And amongſt the many temporall maledictions, which God promiſeth to ſend vpon that Nation which ſhall forſake his Word and Law, to follow humane inuentions, and policies for Religion: this is one, That <hi>the ſtranger that liueth with thee in the Land</hi> (a fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 43.</note> after mans inuentions as thy ſelfe) <hi>ſhall aſcend ouer thee, and ſhalbe higher, and thou ſhalt deſcend downward, and be inferiour. He ſhalbe as the head, and thou ſhalt be as the tayle.</hi> Whereupon the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after they had embraced <hi>Ieroboams</hi> policies for Religion, were <hi>deliuered into the hand of the ſpoilers, vntill God threw them away from his face, euen now from that time</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>when</hi> Iſrael <hi>was rent from the houſe of</hi> Dauid, <hi>and made</hi> Ieroboam <hi>the ſon of</hi> Nabat <hi>their King, for</hi> Ieroboam <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated</hi> Iſrael <hi>from our Lord, and made them to ſin a great ſin,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And</hi> Iſrael <hi>was tranſported out of their Land, vnto</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">4. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>the Aſſirians,</hi> and made ſlaues and tayles vnto thoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, with whom, not long before, they had made couenants of aſſociation and defence. So the whole people of the Iewes renouncing our Sauiour, the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> are as we ſee by experience, euen vntill this day,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16729:48"/> the tayle of all people, and vnder all, and aboue none. Many people and Nations forſaking the Catholike Roman Faith, to embrace Arianiſme, became tayle to the barbarous <hi>Goathes: Africa</hi> infected with the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Donatus,</hi> was conquered by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andals.</hi> The <hi>Eaſt Church,</hi> which whiles it was Chriſtian Catholike, held the Empire of the world, now for her Schiſme is become ſlaue and tayle to the <hi>Turke:</hi> and many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> which heretofore haue flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed vnder the Catholike Roman Faith, by forſaking it, either became baſe, vile, and contemptible, or quite extinct, to the verifying of the words of God, ſaying: <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall glorifie me, I will glorifie him; and they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 2. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>that contemne me ſhelbe baſe.</hi> And who is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the preſent maledictions which are fallen vpon <hi>Germanie,</hi> by forſaking in this our age the Catholike Roman Faith? Since before it flouriſhed both in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and proſperitie aboue all the Nations of the Weſt, which now is puniſhed with all the plagues of God, as Famine, Peſtilence, Sects, Ciuill warre, and in danger to be ſwallowed vp by the <hi>Turke.</hi> And if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the riſing of <hi>Luther,</hi> there euer were any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that made profeſſion of the Religion now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely profeſſed in <hi>England,</hi> as ſome of your Proteſtant Miniſters would ſeeme to affirme; wee ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that they were the tayle, droſſe, and refuſe of all people, ſo lodened with the curſes and maledictions of God, as that there reſteth no more memory of them, then if they neuer had been; to the verifying of the Prophecies, ſaying: <hi>The enemies of our Lord, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>as they ſhalbe honored, and exalted, vaniſhing ſhall vaniſh as ſmoake.</hi> Againe, <hi>I haue ſeene the impious light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>exalted, and aduanced as the Cedars of Libanus. And I paſſed by, and behold he was not: and I ſought him, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>his place was not found.</hi> Againe, <hi>the vniust ſhall periſh</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:16729:48"/> 
                  <hi>together, the remaynes of the impious ſhall periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God Almightie hauing created all creatures, and giuen to euery creature whatſoeuer good it hath, and to certaine Kingdomes and people, particular diuine fauours and graces, aboue other people; as the Faith planted vpon earth by his onely Sonne, by the practiſe whereof, they may liue vpon earth, like Citizens of Saints, and domeſticals of God, and euen in this life, taſte of the comforts and conſolations of diuine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: when this people in ſtead of gratitude, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo baſe and vile, as to forſake this Faith, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the crafty inuentions and politick deuices of men: Then ſaith MOYSES, <hi>Our Lord will not forgiue him:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>but then his fury will moſt ſpecially fume, and his zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that man, and all the curſes ſit vpon him written in</hi> Deutronomie. <hi>And the generation following ſhall ſay; and the children that ſhalbe borne from henceforth, and the ſtranger that ſhal come from a farre. And al the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſeeing the plagues of that Land, ſhal ſay: Why hath the Lord done this to this Land? And they ſhal anſwere: Becauſe they forſooke the couenant of the Lord, which hee made with their Fathers, therefore the fury of the Lord was wrath againſt this Land, to bring vpon it all the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes written in</hi> Deutronomie. <hi>That the iuſt may ſee and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>feare, and ſay; Behold the man, that hath not put God for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>his helper: Behold, they that make them farre from thee,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhal periſh: thou haſt deſtroyed all that Fornicate from thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, they are Lawes and Statutes made againſt all Law, and the grounds of Law: for that Proteſtants would not be content, that the Catholike Kings of <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Polonie,</hi> who haue many Proteſtant ſubjects, ſhould make Proteſtantiſme treaſon or felonie: yet as our Sauiour ſaith: <hi>Whatſoeuer you wil that men do to you,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>doe you alſo to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16729:49"/>
               <p> And to conclude, the precident of making or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing ſuch Lawes followed, will ſerue to make any thing Fellony or Treaſon, or to change the Monarchie into a Common-wealth, or to ſet vp any Intender, or Vſurper: whereof your Highneſſe ought to haue eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care, both for the good of your Perſon, Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and Kingdomes; ouer which, God of his goodneſſe grant, that your <hi>Maiestie</hi> and your Poſteritie may moſt happily Reigne, in the eſtate of Monarkes and abſolute Kings, vnto the worlds end.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>The faults eſcaped I leaue to the courteous Reader to correct.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16729:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
